<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good tydings for sinners, great ioy for saints; or, A word to the world, and two to those that are chosen out of the world. Wherein is held forth, first, the sweet tenders of grace from the father through the son to all dejected sinners; he invites them, he woes them, he intreats them, nay, he beseecheth them to accept of mercy. In the second part of this book, called, Two words to those chosen out of the world, is spoken to the saints under their severall forms, taking notice first of the things commendable in them: and in the second place reproving them for things amisse among them. With a short prophesie of the downfall of presbyterie, independencie, anabaptismie, vaine notions, free-will. With a brief description of a true church-state, against which the gates of Hell shall not prevaile; it being founded upon a rock, it will stand against all waves and storms, that either men or devils can raise against it. I will give you all one heart, and one way. Then the Lord shall be one, and his name one. / Robert Purnell.</title>
            <author>Purnell, Robert, d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91475</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P542</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4234</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E557_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27528</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872168</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872168</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165154</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91475)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165154)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 86:E557[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good tydings for sinners, great ioy for saints; or, A word to the world, and two to those that are chosen out of the world. Wherein is held forth, first, the sweet tenders of grace from the father through the son to all dejected sinners; he invites them, he woes them, he intreats them, nay, he beseecheth them to accept of mercy. In the second part of this book, called, Two words to those chosen out of the world, is spoken to the saints under their severall forms, taking notice first of the things commendable in them: and in the second place reproving them for things amisse among them. With a short prophesie of the downfall of presbyterie, independencie, anabaptismie, vaine notions, free-will. With a brief description of a true church-state, against which the gates of Hell shall not prevaile; it being founded upon a rock, it will stand against all waves and storms, that either men or devils can raise against it. I will give you all one heart, and one way. Then the Lord shall be one, and his name one. / Robert Purnell.</title>
                  <author>Purnell, Robert, d. 1666.</author>
                  <author>Parnell, Robert, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48, 57-75 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Giles Calvert, and are to bee sold at the Black-spread Eagle at the West end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Erroneously attributed to Robert Parnell in Wing P542.</note>
                  <note>Text continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Identified as both Wing P542 and as Wing P4234.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library (Thomason Tracts) and the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University (Early English books).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165154:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Good Tydings for SINNERS, Great Ioy for SAINTS;</p>
            <p>OR, <hi>A Word to the World, and two to thoſe that are choſen out of the</hi> WORLD.</p>
            <p>Wherein is held forth, Firſt, the ſweet tenders of grace from the Father through the Son to all dejected Sinners; he Invites them, he Woes them, he Intreats them, nay, he beſeecheth them to accept of mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IN</hi> The ſecond part of this Book, called, Two words to thoſe choſen out of the World, is ſpoken to the Saints under their ſeverall Forms, taking notice firſt of the things commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable in them: and in the ſecond place reproving them for things amiſſe among them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a ſhort Propheſie of the downfall of</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Presbyterie,</item>
                  <item>Independencie,</item>
                  <item>Anabaptiſmie,</item>
                  <item>Vaine Notions,</item>
                  <item>Free-Will.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With a brief deſcription of a true Church-ſtate, againſt which the gates of Hell ſhall not prevaile; it being founded upon a rock, it will ſtand againſt all Waves and Storms, that either Men or Devils can raiſe againſt it.</p>
            <q>
               <l>I will give you all one heart, and one way.</l>
               <l>Then the Lord ſhall be one, and his name one.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Robert Purnell.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvers,</hi> and are to bee ſold at the Black-ſpread Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:165154:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165154:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, I ſhall in few words give thee a juſt accompt, why I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this little Book In theſe latter daies many books are publiſhed, ſome good and wholeſome: but few to ends not carnal; for with every man is imperfection more or leſſe, I muſt own it alſo. Yet I faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully profeſſe, that had my own credit or advantage been my inducement hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, theſe thoughts had been buried in the wombe; becauſe I know, I could reap no ſuch fruit; or if I did, it were but vanitie. He that gave me my being, hath given me a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to learn of him; not onely to love his people, but alſo to love his enemies, <hi>Matth. 5.44.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God having kindled in me, a love to you both Saints and Sinners; I have here written a word to the one, and two words to the other: <hi>Rom. 1.14.</hi> I am debtor to the Greek, and to the Barbarian, both to the wiſe, and to the unwiſe:</p>
            <p>And to thee fellow ſinner, is the firſt word; becauſe I ſee many of thoſe that undertake to teach thee, ſhutting the door of the kingdom againſt thee; and inſtead of the Goſpel of Chriſt, they preach to thee <hi>Moſes,</hi> at leaſt <hi>Elias;</hi> and that in the letter. The things I lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, and commend unto thee; are ſuch, and onely ſuch, as I my ſelf have paſt through, and found aboundance of comfort in: And looking upon that place <hi>2 Corinth. 1.4.</hi> I finde it my duty to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to comfort others with the ſame comfort wherewith I my ſelfe have been comforted of God.</p>
            <p>Expect not heare a pleaſing methode, ſugard words, nor ſchola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall
<pb facs="tcp:165154:3"/>expreſſions; for that ſavours more of the wiſdome of man than of God. Though it be not ſcholaſtick yet if thou findest it authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick; let it have acceptance with thee. Firſt read, and then judge of what I have ſaid; and the Lord that hath power, give thee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in all things.</p>
            <p>In the firſt part of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k called, <hi>A Word to the World,</hi> is held forth in few words; the ſweet tenders of grace from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through the ſonne, to the poore dejected Sinners; wherein God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, woes, and entreates them to be reconciled to himſelfe. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſwers all the Objections that lye in the way, he uſeth very ſtrong and powerfull arguments: He not onely ſaith but ſwears, he delights not in the death of a ſinner, <hi>Ezek. 33.11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond part of this Book called, <hi>Two Words to thoſe cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of the World;</hi> I my ſelf having had communion with the Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in each of thoſe forms, more or leſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their principles and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes I have in ſome meaſure weighed, examined, and tryed with an unbyaſſed affection: And I finde among all theſe (except thoſe in this book excepted) many excellent, ſweet, and ſound truths, both in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline, Principle and Practiſe, worthy not onely of commendation, but alſo of our imitation.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding, there are many things that ſavour more of the fleſh than of the ſpirit among all theſe Aſſemblies, which are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mans invention than of Gods inſtitution: as their knowing Chriſt and Saints after the fleſh; crying, Lo here, lo there is Chriſt; and moſt in a ſence building upon the Sand. Wherefore I have here Propheſied of their fall, in which I mean not that they ſhall be without Church-order; but they ſhall have Paſtors and Teachers, Elders and Deacons, Helps and Governments. But the ground of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion ſhall be ſpirituall union: and when this day is dawned, and this day-ſtar riſen in our hearts, <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſhall not envy <hi>Judah,</hi> nor <hi>Judah</hi> vex <hi>Ephraim; Presbyterians</hi> ſhall not ſo bitterly cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Independents,</hi> nor <hi>Independents</hi> have ſuch hard thoughts of the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> Yea, they will be aſhamed to own one another by theſe fleſhly titles; but look upon and love one another as Chriſtians, members of the ſame body, heires of the ſame Promiſe, children of the ſame father: having all the ſame ſpirit, all clothed with the ſame robe, inclined to the ſame work; ruled by the ſame Word and Spirit. And ſo their love to each other ſhall ariſe from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in the Spirit. And againſt this Church-State the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165154:3"/>
            <head>A <hi>WORD</hi> TO THE VVORLD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Sin had its firſt entrance into the World by <hi>Adam,</hi> we all know; What ſin is in it own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, moſt of us doe know; But that ſin is clearly taken away by the ſecond <hi>Adam, Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> that, very few doe know.</p>
            <p>Poore ſinner, why doſt thou lye groaning, come along with me, and hear Chriſt thy Lord ſpeaking to thee.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is that that doth ſo trouble thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Oh! my ſins, my ſin.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is ſin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The breach of a command, or the tranſgreſſion of a law.</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Though thou haſt broken this law,</hi> yet conſider, that there is one to be found, that hath kept it; firſt, in thy nature: ſecondly, for thee, and imputes the keeping of it to thee, as really, as if thou hadſt fulfilled it thy ſelfe; Art thou a ſinner? Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He came to call ſinners, and why not thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sinner,</hi> Oh, but I am one of the greateſt of ſinners.</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Yet conſider what the Lord ſaith in theſe Scriptures, Joh.</hi> 1.29 Behold the Lamb of God, that taketh away the ſins of the World. 3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. God ſo loved the World, that he ſent his onely begotten Son, to take away the ſins of the world. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. He came into
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165154:4"/>the world to ſinners, of whom I am chief.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Oh, but though he came to ſave ſinners, it is a queſtion, whether he died for all ſinners, and therefore I queſtion, whether he came to call me, or to take away my ſins, I ſee no ground why I ſhould believe; nay, I cannot believe, Faith is too high a thing for me to attain unto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But conſider, God is the alone worker of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. And when thou lookeſt upon Faith, and ſeeſt it too hard a thing for thee; yet conſider that nothing is too hard for God, who hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to work it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> It I could ſee a promiſe wherein God had promiſed to work it, that were ſomething.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What art thou? A</hi> Jew <hi>or a</hi> Gentile, Scythian <hi>or</hi> Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I am a <hi>Gentile,</hi> a ſinner.</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Thou theſe are promiſes for thee, ſee Matt.</hi> 12.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.12. In him ſhall the Gentiles truſt, in him ſhall the Gentiles truſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> But all Gentiles doe not, neither ſhall they believe; therefore if I could ſee my name written in Scripture, and a promiſe made to me in reference to that name, then there were hope indeed.</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Thou art juſt like</hi> Thomas, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.25. Except I ſhall ſee in his hands the print of the nailes, and thruſt my hand into his ſide; I will not believe: <hi>Well, ſaith Chriſt, thou ſhalt ſee the print of the nailes, reach hither thine hand,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Wilt thou ſee thy name inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture indeed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> Yea, with all my heart, But I fear it is not there.</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Why doſt thou doubt? all things are poſſible to him that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves: wilt thou ſee thy name? Then what is thy ſtate? How is it with thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> My ſtate is miſerable, I am full of blindenes and ignorance, and can underſtand nothing in a ſpirituall way.</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Here is thy name then recorded, Iſa.</hi> 50.10. Who ſo walketh in darknes and ſeeth no light, let him truſt in the name of the Lord, and ſtay upon God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> But I am dead almoſt, my heart and my fleſh do faile me.</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Why, canſt thou read the beginning of the verſe</hi> (<hi>with</hi> David) <hi>and not the latter end of it,</hi> and God is the ſtrength of my heart, and my portion for ever: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> But I am weak (faith another poore ſoule) where is my name?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:165154:4"/>Chr. <hi>The weak ſhall be as</hi> David, <hi>there is thy name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> But ſaith another diſtreſſed ſoule, I am quite dead; where is my name?</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.14. Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee light: <hi>There is thy name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> But I have not ears to hear Chriſt voice, nor ſtrength to ariſe; if I could hear.</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>But Chriſt can give ſtrength with his voice, as to</hi> Lazarus, come forth, <hi>and he came forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> Here is comfort for theſe indeed; But oh! that you could ſhew me my name, in ſcripture, and God ſpeaking to me by name; Then I ſhould believe and rejoyce with joy unſpeakable and full of glory.</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Well: What is thy name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> Rebell; That is my name; for I have rebelled againſt the Lord ever ſince I was born; I have lived in a continuall breach of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very command.</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Yet behold thy name, Pſal.</hi> 68.18. Chriſt hath received gifts for men; yea, for the rebellious, that the Lord God might dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them: <hi>Read thy name in every promiſe, endeavour to ſee thy name enrolled in the book of Life, where all the Devils in Hell, and all the wicked men in the world can never blot it out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> Oh! ſaith another poore diſtreſſed ſoule, I have no minde, nor heart to ſeek after God, Where is my name?</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Iſa</hi> 65.1. I am found of them that ſought me not, <hi>There is thy name: though thou wilt not ſeek for him, yet he will ſeek and</hi> finde thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> But I cannot believe; Where is my name, ſaith another?</p>
            <p>Chr. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 13. If we believe not, yet he abideth faithfull, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> But I have called and cryed for mercy, and that often, yet God would not anſwer me: Where is my name?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Saith another, others have prayed for me, and the Lord gave them an anſwer; he was not ſent to ſave me: Where is my name?</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third poore ſoul ſteps in, and ſaith, I ſpake with the Lord, as it were, and he told me, I was a Dog; and that Dogs have nothing to doe with Childrens bread; oh, where is my name?</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Will you ſee all your three names together?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin.</hi> Oh that it might be ſo, faith the troubled ſoule.</p>
            <p>Chr. <hi>Then read and well conſider that</hi> 15. <hi>Matt.</hi> 22, 23, 24, 25,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165154:5"/>26, 27, 28. And behold a woman of Canaan came out of the ſame coaſts, and cryed unto him, ſaying; have mercy on me O Lord, thou ſon of <hi>David:</hi> But he anſwered her not a word: <hi>There was the firſt ſtep of his deniall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>His Diſciples came and beſought him, ſaying, ſend her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, for ſhe cryeth after us. But he anſwered and ſaid, I am not ſent but unto the loſt ſheep of the houſe Iſrael.</hi> There is the ſecond branch of his deniall.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. <hi>Then came ſhee, and worſhipped him ſaying: Lord help me, But he anſwered and ſaid, it is not meet to take the childrens bread and caſt it to dogs:</hi> There is the third branch of his deniall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſhe ſaid, truth Lord: yet the dogs eat of the crumbs that fall from their Maſters table: Then Jeſus anſwered and ſaid unto her; ô woman, great is thy faith; be it unto thee even as thou wilt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh the unſearchable love of a tender father, to a prodigall Son!</p>
            <p>To ſumme up all in a word; Search diligently in what ſtate thou ſtandeſt, examine well thy preſent condition what it is: and when thou haſt found out the true temper of thy ſoul; <hi>that thou canſt tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, thus and thus it is with me:</hi> Then ſearch the Scriptures, for they were written for thy learning; and thou ſhalt finde upon ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration, that ſome one or other of the Saints (gone before the) hath been in the ſame condition, and yet hath found mercy: Then thou wilt break forth with <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſay, <hi>There is no tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath befaln me, but ſuch as is common to all men, and the Lord will deliver mee.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 13. &amp;c. Are thy ſins ſo many that thou canſt not look up! ſo it was with that pretious ſaint, <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 40.12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deare friend,</hi> who ever thou art that readeſt theſe words, let me tell thee, I ſpeak by experience; I have been in ſo ſad a condition, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as it were in deſpaire: And when I have read or heard theſe words, that ſuch and ſuch of the Lords own children, were in the ſame condition; my heart hath begun to revive and ſay, well: The Lord hath dealt no otherwiſe with me, than he hath with ſuch a Saint left upon record: now I ſee, I am not alone in this heavines, I cannot now ſay; <hi>Was ever ſorrow like unto my ſorrow.</hi> Lam. 1.12. But I can now ſay with <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> Lam. 3 32. <hi>Though he cauſe griefe, yet will he have compaſſion, according to the multitude of his mercies.</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that ſweet place of Scripture: 2 Cor. 1 3, 4. <hi>Bleſſed be God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Father of mercies, and the God of all comfort, who comforteth us in all our tribulations,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165154:5"/>that</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we may be able to comfort them that be in trouble, by the comfort wherewith wee our ſelves are comforted of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here by the way wee may take notice, that it is a duty well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the Saints, to endeavour as inſtruments in Gods hands, to comfort others with the ſame comforts, wherewith the Lord hath comforted them, <hi>Come</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> David) <hi>I will tell thee what the Lord hath done for my ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe: Oh thou drooping ſinner, liſten a little unto the voyce of Chriſt, and thou ſhalt heare him calling to thee and ſaying, <hi>Come come unto mee all yee that bee weary and heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> Hee cals thee, hee invites thee, hee entreates thee, hee beſeecheth thee to come in, and to bee reconciled unto the Lord thy God. See and conſider well that Scripture 2. Cor. 5 20. <hi>Now then wee are ambaſſadours for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us, wee pray you in Chriſt ſtead bee you reconciled unto God,</hi> you ſee hee is willing to have ſinners reconciled to him, and that hee doth manifeſt, by many demonſtrations, or evidences.</p>
            <p>Firſt, His patience towards thee all this while, he is long ſuffering, not willing that any ſhould periſh 2 Pet. 3 9. Rom. 2.4. <hi>The goodneſſe of God, or the patience of God doth (or ſhould) lead thee to repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Hee doth manifeſt his willingneſſe, in that hee hath made this the maſter-piece of all his works, to provide a Saviour for us: in ſending his Son, and making him a curſe for us, in this great worke the Lord doth proclaime to all the world, <hi>Oh all you people of the world, if I had not beene willing to bee reconciled to you,</hi> or rather, to have you reconciled to mee, (as I have for ever beene) I would never have ſent my deareſt Sonne from the boſome of my love, to die for you. So that this is the greateſt worke; all my other workes are ſubordinate to this. <hi>In this was the love of God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to us, that he ſent his onely begotten Sonne into the world, that we ſhould live through him,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.9.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Lord doth profeſſe this to the people, That there is no one thing wherein hee doth more glory, than to ſhew mercy to poore ſinners, yea to his enemies. Micah 7.18. <hi>Hee delighteh in mercy.</hi> Exod. 34. <hi>The Lords glory paſſed by,</hi> and what was that? <hi>The Lord, the Lord, moſt mercifull and gratious, long ſuffering</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pardoning iniquity, tranſgreſſions and ſinne.</hi> Here is my glory. <hi>Hence it is expreſt,</hi> Iſa. 30.18. <hi>Therefore will the Lord waite that hee may bee gratious, and therefore will hee bee exalted that hee may
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165154:6"/>have mercy upon you.</hi> So then, the Lord doth accompt himſelfe, an exalted God, when hee hath brought in a ſinner to accept of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Lord doth expreſſe his willingneſſe even with a ſigh (as it were) which doth much denote his willingneſſe, Deut. 5.29. <hi>Oh that there were ſuch an heart in them, that they would feare, my Name and keepe my Commands,</hi> and that for one good too, for ſo the words follow, <hi>that it might be well with them, and with their children for ever.</hi> Now theſe people had ſaid before, <hi>whatſoever the Lord hath ſpoken wee will doe. Oh that there were ſuch an heart in them (ſaith the Lord.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, The Lord doth expreſſe his willingneſſe with an oath too, and that, the greateſt that ever hee tooke; That ſinners ſhall not dye. Ezek. 33.10, 11. <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turne from his way and live. Turne yee, turne yee from your evill wayes, for why will you die, oh houſe of</hi> Iſraell &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, God doth manifeſt his willingneſſe in this; that above all other workes, this worke of beleeving on him, is moſt pleaſing to him, and our not beleeving, is the greateſt offence that wee can give to God, Joh. 6.29. <hi>This is the worke of God, that you beleeve on him whom he hath ſent,</hi> as if the Lord had ſaid, <hi>This doth pleaſe mee better than any other worke,</hi> Let a poore ſoule come in, and rowle himſelfe upon the love of God in Chriſt, for reconciliation. This is a more glorious worke, than the conquering of a whole world; If you give all your goods to the poore, and your bodies to be burnt, all is nothing if this be wanting. Joh. 3.19. <hi>This is condemnation that light is come unto the world, and men love darkneſſe more then light.</hi> In a word, binde all your ſinnes together in a bundle, (except this ſin of unbeliefe) and put them in a ballance together, And put this ſin of unbeliefe in the other ballance, you ſhall finde that unbeliefe will weigh downe all the reſt, and from this unbeliefe, as the roote, ſprings all other evils, as the branches.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Conſider further, God doth ſeeke to ſinners firſt: Therefore it is ſaid, The Lord Chriſt came to ſeeke <hi>and to ſave them that were loſt.</hi> Iſa. 45.22. <hi>Looke unto me and be you ſaved all yee ends of the earth, the Spirit and the Bride ſay come, and let him that is a thirſt come and take of the waters of life freely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eightly, Conſider, the Lord ſends forth his grace to allure thee and to entice thee, a ſinner, to come to him, Hee doth with cords of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165154:6"/>love draw the heart to come, Hee ſends forth his mercy to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſoule, and tender its ſervice (as it were) to the ſinfull ſoule, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.14. <hi>Therefore will I allure them ſaith the Lord.</hi> There was a great breach betweene this people and God, as you may ſee at large in this chapter, And yet ſaith the Lord <hi>I will allure them</hi> Hoſea 11.4. <hi>I will draw them with the cords of men: with the bands of love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly, The Lord is ſo yeelding unto his creatures, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to keepe his owne honour and glory he cannot yeeld further. At firſt, wee are all going aſtray, the Lord cals us backe. 2. Wee were going to priſon, The Lord ſteps in, ſaying, I will provide a ſurety. The Covenant of workes requires ſatisfaction, ſaith the Lord, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to take this, in a ſurety. Wee are like a Beggar, begging an almes of one that paſſeth by, to whom it is anſwered, I will give thee oh Beggar that which thou deſireſt, but thou muſt come and fetch it: I cannot come ſaith the Beggar, I want legs: I will give thee legs (ſaith the giver) that thou mayeſt come. But ſaith the Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, when I am come, I have no hands to receive that which you will give me: I will give thee hands alſo. Oh! But I want wiſedome to make uſe of that gift: I will give thee wiſedome ſaith the Lord. Oh that ever, ſo glorious a God, ſhould ſo farre ſtoope and yeeld to his poore creatures, as to anſwer all queſtions, cleare all doubts, and take away all ſcruples!</p>
            <p>Tenthly, He yet comes nearer to a ſinner (as it were) and doth profeſſe, that the greateſt ſins that ever they have committed againſt him, ſhall not hinder them from comming to him, nor him from par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning them. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.18, <hi>Come now and let us reaſon together, ſaith the Lord. though your ſins be as Scarlet, they ſhalbe as white as Snow.</hi> Oh here the Lord proclaimes <hi>that all thy ſinnes paſt ſhall bee done away, Thy continuance in ſinne</hi> will be thy undoing, if any thing.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, Againe Conſider, The Lord doth in his Word uſe very powerfull arguments, to draw the heart to bee reconciled to him; Hee doth not onely offer mercy, and ſet it before the ſoule, but he doth labour with ſtrong reaſons, and arguments, and motives, to draw the ſoule to himſelfe, and doth uſe theſe arguments, that will take the heart moſt. Sometimes hee doth draw arguments from his equity. Ezekiel 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. <hi>Are not my wayes equall ſaith the Lord.</hi> Sometimes from our nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſity. Joh. 3.36. <hi>Hee that beleeveth not, the wrath of God abideth on him.</hi> Sometimes from the benefit
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165154:7"/>and profit we ſhall have, if we do come in; Prov. 1.23. <hi>Turn yee at my reproof, and behold I will powre out my Spirit upon you, I will make known my words unto you.</hi> Oh bleſſed promiſe! one would think, this ſhould break the heart of Devils; as if the Lord had ſaid, well, though thou haſt been a great ſinner, and though thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled againſt me ever ſince thou waſt born; yet if thou wilt but turn at my reproof, or ſay to thy God, Turn us and we ſhal be turned, (for I muſt doe it) I will powre out my Spirit upon thee, I will give grace and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ory, a Houſe, a City, a Kingdome, Light, Life, and all things: The Lord doth ſeem to out-bid all other comforts that we have in ſin; therefore he doth tell us of honey, milk, raiment, ſuch things as do moſt take with our hearts, that ſo he might gain us to come in and be at one with him. Now I ſhall appeal to your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that have felt this in ſome meaſure: Doth not the Devill come with ſtrong arguments? The World with the like? And wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men with ſtrong perſwaſions? The corruptions within you with ſtrong motives? And yet doth not the Lord out-bid them all, and ſo win the Soule to himſelf.</p>
            <p>Twelfth, Conſider further, The Lord comes and anſwers all obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that lye in the hearts of ſinners.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> 1. Saith one I am unworthy; I have nothing in me that good is:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Lord ſaith, Iſa. 55. <hi>Come and buy milk and wine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out money, and without price,</hi> three times it is ſpoken in one or two verſes. So that God doth ſet forth his kingdome by milke, wine and bread, things uſefull for the body; ſometimes by a marriage, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by a ſupper, wherein are all kindes of dainties; ſometime he doth invite them to the ſupper, and to the marriage of his Sonne, and ſometimes doth compell them to come in. Then the Devil working with our corrupt nature; doth what he can to make the Soule ſlight the Goſpel, and to look upon the blood of the Covenant as a mean thing: When the ſoul doth begin indeed to apprehend the greatnes and ſweetnes of the Goſpel of glad tidings, then ſteps in Sathan; What ſuch a one as thou have ſuch mercy? Fellow ſinners; mark the policy of the ſubtle Devil, he doth at firſt labor to ſet at naught the Goſpel, accounting it as a mean thing: But when the Lord doth ſhine through that miſt, and ſhew the ſoul the excellency of his ſon, and the glory of the Goſpel: Then comes the devil the other way, ſaying, with thee theſe be great things indeed; But thou art vile and baſe both in thy principles &amp; practice: and canſt thou think that God ever intended
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165154:7"/>theſe things to thee? <hi>What to ſuch a one as thou art;</hi> Then the Lord anſwereth for thee, <hi>Come without money and without price,</hi> as if he had ſaid, though thou haſt no ability to doe any thing; yet come I will make thee rich enough; thou haſt no money (that is no ſelf righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes) let not that hinder, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17. <hi>The Spirit and the Bride ſay come, and let him that bears come, and let him that is a thirſt come, and whoſoever will let him take of the water of life free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> It may be (ſaith the Soule, though the Lord doth require no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before hand; yet when I am come he will require hard things of me, I muſt live ſo ſtrictly, and abandon all my pleaſures, what? ſhall I leave all thoſe pleaſant wayes, and have nothing but according to the word, and according to conſcience; Then farewell all the comfort and joy of all our life, if we come to this once.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I appeale to you, whether your hearts have not been kept of by ſuch things as theſe. But now <hi>(ó fellow ſinners)</hi> mark how Chriſt doth take off theſe objections, Matth. 11. <hi>Come unto me and I will give you reſt. Take my yoke upon you</hi> (and mark what follows) <hi>my yoke is eaſie and my burthen light.</hi> As if Chriſt ſhould ſay, I will lay no yoak upon you but what is eaſie, nor any burthen but what is light. And this I affirme, though this may ſeem to be hard to you at firſt; you will finde the wayes of God more eaſie than ever you found the wayes of ſin: Do but ask them that have any experience of the love of God to them, and they will tell thee; that they have found more ſweetneſſe in one day, in following of God, than they found in the wayes of ſin many years: Prov. 3.17. <hi>Her wayes are wayes of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſſe, and all her paths are peaceable paths:</hi> Now if you will believe the ſpirit of God, you ſee there is more peace, more joy, more ſweetneſſe, more comfort than ever you had before.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Again conſider, The Lord doth not onely uſe ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and anſwer all objections. But he is importunate too, as firſt; He doth cry out after ſinners; Prov. 1. <hi>Wiſdome cryeth in the ſtreets,</hi> and ſo Prov. 9. and Iſa. 55. He doth make Proclamation, <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth come!</hi> He doth importune, and bid come, over and over again, and again; <hi>Come, come, come,</hi> three times together: So that God doth ſeek more earneſtly to ſinners, than they doe to him. It may be thou wilt ſeek to God once for a mercy thou wanteſt, and give over; But behold, God cals to thee again and again, <hi>come, come, come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:165154:8"/>14. If all this will not prevaile with ſinners to come in, yet the Lord leaves them not, but appeals to the very Conſciences of ſinners, &amp; deals with them that way. If you were in great diſtreſſe concerning your eſtate or life, and you go to a man that hath both wiſdom and power to help you; and open the caſe to him, but cannot prevaile: then you bring ſtrong arguments; and they do not move, then you take away all objections: but yet prevaile not; then you importune him, and urge your arguments againe and again; and all this doth not prevaile; then you appeale to his own conſcience whether you have not ſpoken right to him, ſaying; I will even leave this to your own conſcience to judge of it; and this many times doth prevaile when no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing elſe will: even thus (of all the world) doth God deal with ſinners and appeals to their own conſciences. Iſa. 43.26. <hi>Put me in remembrance: let us plead together. Declare thou that thou mayeſt be juſtified:</hi> as if the Lord had ſaid, If thou canſt declare any thing why thou doeſt not come, that lyeth in thy way, I will remove it, and thou ſhalt be accepted. Ier. 2.5. Thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>What iniquity have your Fathers found in me, that they are gone farre from me.</hi> Verſ 31. <hi>Have I been a barren wilderneſſe to Iſrael.</hi> Ezek. 18.25. <hi>Hear now ô houſe of Iſrael, are not my ways equall? are not your waies unequall?</hi> as if the Lord had ſaid, doe you think in your conſcience, that theſe wayes that you walk in are right? Is this equall, that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhould go on their dayes and paſſe their time in ſin; and when they can ſin no longer, then to plead for mercy: Is this equall? If this will not doe, the Lord will ſay, Conſcience let him alone; So con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may be quiet, but the Lord hath left pleading with him.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Again, the Lord hath many times brake forth into tears to ſee the ſtubborneſſe of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns hearts: <hi>O Jeruſalem, thou that killeſt the Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>if thou hadſt known in this thy day the things that make for thy peace.</hi> Now ſuppoſe that Chriſt ſhould come and weep over a company of poore ſinners, as he did over Jeruſalem, ſaying, ô thou ſinfull ſoule, hadſt thou known in this thy day, the things that belong to thy peace, and ſuppoſe thou ſhouldeſt ſee one tear trickling down after another, and he ſhould ſay; Oh, that this people did but know the things that belong unto their peace: If thou hadſt a heart of ſtone, it could not but melt.</p>
            <p n="16">16. The Lord doth foreſee, what a little honour hee ſhall have of this ſinner when he hath brought him home; he ſeeth ſtill that thou wilt have abundance of corruption in thy heart, and that thou wilt grieve his holy Spirit, and walk very offenſively, diſhonour the way
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165154:8"/>of Religion, and open the mouths of the enemies as <hi>David;</hi> I ſay, God doth foreſee, that after he hath taken all this pains to bring thee unto himſelf, what a little honour he ſhall have by thee, and yet he doth perſwade thee to come: This alſo doth note his willingneſſe to ſave thee.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, conſider, that after the Lord our tender Father hath uſed all theſe means and many more to bring in ſinners; yet he is conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to waite a long time upon ſinners, and to take advantages to win them. Iſa. 30.18. <hi>The Lord doth waite that he may be gracious unto you.</hi> O how many years hath the Lord waited upon me, and thee, and other ſinners: How long hath he knocked, and yet we let him ſtand at the doore. <hi>O Jeruſalem wilt thou not be made clean, when ſhall it once be.</hi> Iſa. 51.17, 18. <hi>I ſmote him, and he went on frowardly; but I have ſeen his waies, and will heal him, and reſtore comfort to him, and to his mourners.</hi> Though he went on frowardly, I will reſtore comfort to him.</p>
            <p>Now put all this together, and ſee how infinitely willing God is to ſave thee, ô thou drowping ſinner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> If any ſhould ask a reaſon, why God is ſo importunate and deſirous to draw up ſinners to himſelf?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The ground of this love is in himſelf, and I can give no reaſon of it, but the ſame that he hath left upon record, Exod. 33.19. <hi>I will be gracious to whom I will be gracious, and will ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on whom I will ſhew mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He doth this, becauſe mercy pleaſeth him: Micah. 7.18. <hi>I will pardon becauſe mercie pleaſeth mee,</hi> ſaith the Lord; Now then, that that doth pleaſe a man, he is ever deſirous after: The ſcripture ſaith, <hi>He doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the children of men;</hi> but hee ſheweth mercy willingly, becauſe he delighteth in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The blood of Chriſt his onely ſonne doth cry aloud in the ears of the Lord for mercy; and that obedience of Chriſt wherewith the Lord is ſatisfied, is ſo well pleaſing to him, that whatſoever this blood doth plead for, God muſt needs grant: Now the blood of Chriſt, cryeth mercy, mercy Lord, for ſinners; the blood of <hi>Abel</hi> cryed vengeance, vengeance; but the blood of Chriſt ſpeaketh bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, and cryeth pardon, pardon. Nothing in the world can ſtop the current of Gods mercy to a people, when it doth come to the blood of Chriſt; Then ſaith the father of mercies, open all the flood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates now, and let mercy be ſhewed in the higheſt degree; ſeeing the blood of my ſonne cryeth for this: though this be wonderfull
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165154:9"/>mercy to pardon ſuch a great ſinner, there is not a drop onely, but a Sea of mercy, to cleanſe thee throughly. <hi>Come,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>let us reaſon together, though your ſins be as ſcarlet; they ſhall be as white as Snow.</hi> Iſa. 1 18. <hi>I, even I am he that blotteth out thy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions for my own name ſake, and will not remember. thy ſins.</hi> Iſa. 43 25. <hi>Put me in remembrance, ſaith the Lord, put me in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of this my promiſe, and let us plead together,</hi> ſaith the Lord; <hi>Declare theſe words with thy mouth, that I have put into thy heart, that thou mayeſt be juſtified.</hi> Iſa. 43.26.</p>
            <p>O thou troubled ſinner (for to thee I ſpeak) I mean thee, to whom ſin is a but then; See how our tender father hath dealt with our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prodigall; <hi>Luke</hi> 15 28. He aroſe and came to his Father; but when he was yet a great way of, his Father ſaw him, and had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on him, and ran, and fell on his neck and kiſſed him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take notice, his father ſees him, before he ſees his Father. No ſooner doth a ſinner think of looking toward heaven, but the Lord ſpyes him and pities him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſaw him whiles he was a great way off; he was but in the beginning of his way to come: his father might have let him alone till he had been come quite home to his houſe, and it had been ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular mercy to have bid him welcome then; but it is done whiles he is a great way off. So thou art at a great diſtance from the mercy of God in thy apprehenſion, that is, thou canſt not believe, nor ſcarce hope in his mercy; yet he will draw nigh to thee.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſcripture ſaith, his father had compaſſion on him: I ſee the Lords bowels yearn, work, and ſtir within him at the ſight of his ſon, Jer. 3.20. <hi>Therefore my bowels are troubled for him, I will ſurely have mercy upon him, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Jer. 9.24. <hi>I delight in loving kindnes,</hi> Mich. 7.18. <hi>He pardoneth becauſe mercy pleaſeth him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It is ſaid, that his father <hi>ran:</hi> How rich, abundant mercy had it been in his father, though he had ſtood ſtill, till his ſon had come to him: <hi>But what mercy is this?</hi> he will go towards him, and give him a meeting; <hi>O mercy!</hi> that his father ran not from him; but what mercy call you this, that he runs to him: Why, would it not have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (if he would needs go meet him) to have walked toward him with a ſoft and grave pace? No, no, that will not ſerve the Lords turn: if a ſinner will but go towards the Lord, mercy will not go a foot-pace, but runs to meet him; yea, mercy draws him and puts him upon comming at firſt-ſtep: The ſonnes pace is, he aroſe and came he came walking towards his father; this is the fathers pace he <hi>ran;</hi> the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165154:9"/>ſonne moſt needed to have run, his belly was pinched with hunger, yet hee onely walkes, but his father runs, bowels full of mercy out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace bowels pinched with hunger.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I ſee him falling upon his necke, that is, he hugg'd and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced him, How? fall on his necke? Who would not have beene loath to have touched him? yea, to come neare him? Is he not in his loathſome ſtinking rags? Smels he not of the Swine hee kept? Could a man come neare him without ſtopping his Noſe? Would not a man bee ready to caſt up his Stomach, upon ſuch an embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Mercy is not nice and dainty, will God thus embrace a Prodigall in his loathſome rags? Oh ſinner be encouraged to draw neare to God, for the worſt of all wickedneſſe and baſeneſſe in the world cannot make him rejct thee. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 16.4 5, 6.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But yet behold, a greater wonder than all the reſt: I ſee him <hi>kiſſing his Sorne;</hi> who could have brooked to have imbraced a perſon, in ſo futhy a pickle? Much leſſe would any one kiſſe ſuch a one; what kiſſe thoſe lips that had beene ſo lately lapping in the Hogs-Trough: Thoſe lips that had ſo often kiſs'd thoſe baſe and beggerly Harlots; <hi>Kiſſe him?</hi> A man would rather have thought he would have kick'd him, and yet his Father kiſſeth him. There is a paſſage ſomewhat like this, Gen. 33.4. <hi>And</hi> Eſau <hi>ran to meet him, and embraced him, and fell on his Neck, and kiſſed him.</hi> A ſtrang and wonderfull thing that hee that had threatned to kill him and came now upon that errand to kill him and all his, That his heart ſhould bee ſo ſtrangely altered by God, that killing ſhould bee turned into kiſſing: It was very ſtrange that <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould kiſſe <hi>Jacoh,</hi> but it is more ſtrange here, that this Father ſhould kiſſe this Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall.</p>
            <p>Read and conſider well theſe Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Joh. 1.29. <hi>Behold the Lambe of God, that taketh away the ſins of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Luke 2.10.11. <hi>Behold I bring you good tydings of great joy, that ſhall bee to all people.</hi> That is, <hi>That unto you is borne this day in the City of</hi> David, <hi>a Saviour which is Chriſt the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>John 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the World that he gave his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son, to this end, that all that beleeve in him ſhould not periſh, but have life everlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>John 3.17. <hi>God ſent not his Son into the world, to condemne the world, but that the world through him might be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:165154:10"/>1 Tim. 1.15. <hi>This is a true ſaying that Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners, of whom I am chiefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heb. 13.12. <hi>Jeſus that he might ſanctifie the people with his own blood, ſuffered without the Gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 John 2.1, 2. <hi>If any man ſinne wee have an Advocate with the Father Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, and hee is the propitiation for our ſins and not for ours onely, but alſo the ſinnes of the whole world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rev. 5.8. <hi>Thou waſt killed and haſt redeemed us to God out of every kindred, tongue and people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pſalm 145.19. <hi>Hee will fulfill the deſire of them that feare him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Zach. 13.1. <hi>The Lord hath opened a Fountaine for ſinne and for uncleanneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He every one that thirſteth come then.</hi> Iſaiah 55.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed are they that bunger and thirſt, for they ſhall be filled.</hi> Math. 5.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any man thirſt, let him come unto mee and drinke.</hi> John 7. ver. 37, 38.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And hee that commeth to me I will in no wiſe caſt off;</hi> oh marke, <hi>I will in no wiſe caſt him off,</hi> John 6.37, that is, there is no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in thee, nor all thy enemies without thee, that ſhall ſo farre prevaile with mee, as that I ſhall forſake thee.</p>
            <p>Oh then come unto mee, come unto mee, <hi>all you that are heavy laden, and I will undoubtedly give you reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider, Hee that hath made theſe promiſes, is able to make them good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hee is not onely able to doe it, but hee is willing to doe it, hee delights in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hee is not only able and willing, but he is faithfull too in keeping promiſe; In ſo much that not one title ſhall faile of all that he hath promiſed: He never ſaith, <hi>Seeke yee me in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Take notice, the Lord keepes open houſe, Rev. 22.17. <hi>Let him that will, come and take of the water of life freely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe of our backwardneſſe to come, he invites, Iſa. 55.1. <hi>He, every one that thirſteth, come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Hee anſwereth objections, and taketh away all excuſes, in theſe words, <hi>come without money and without price,</hi> though thou haſt not righteouſneſſe to commend thee to mee, yet come, <hi>without money and without price.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:165154:10"/>4. He aſſures thee, thou ſhalt be welcome, John 6.37. <hi>Him that commeth to me, I will in no wiſe caſt off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Hee tels thee, that if thou come, thou ſhalt not looſe thy labour, <hi>He will give thee reſt,</hi> Mat. 11.28.</p>
            <p>Hee will give thee reſt from thine owne righteouſneſſe, that thou ſhalt ſee thy acceptance in the righteouſneſſe of another, and ſo ceaſe from thine owne. Hee will give thee reſt, that is, hee will ſtill thoſe troubles that ariſe in thine heart, and take off thoſe veiles from thine eyes, and the bondage that lay upon thy heart, and ſhew thee that he hath ſet the free from hell, death, law, ſinne paſt, preſent, and to come, and ſo gives thee faith, which is the evidence of things not ſeene, which will evidence this to thy ſoule: Thy ſoule no ſooner apprehends this, but preſently it wilbe ready to break forth in theſe words of <hi>Mary,</hi> Luke 1.46, 47, 48. <hi>My Soule doth magnifie the Lord, my Spirit hath rejoyced in God my Saviour: For he hath regarded the low eſtate of his handmaid</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And now to draw to a concluſion (for as I ſaid in the beginning) I have but a Word to the World. 1 He gives free liberty to come. 2. Hee invites thee 3. He will bid thee welcome. 4. He will caſe thee of all thy troubles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But thou wilt ſay, Heare are indeed ſweet rules and bleſſed promiſes amongſt theſe things that you have layd downe. But I have no abillity to walke in the one, nor heart to embrace or beleeve the other, and I finde it written, Jer. 10.23. <hi>The way of man is not in himſelfe, It is not in man that walketh to direct his ſteps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But conſider, hee requires nothing of thee, but what he hath promiſed hee will inable thee to doe. For inſtance, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.16. He requires thee, and ſaith, <hi>waſh thee and make thee cleane, put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the evill of thy doings, ceaſe to doe evill: Learne to doe well.</hi> Here is his precept, and thy duty. Now turne from this precept to that promiſe, Jer. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.8. <hi>I will cleanſe them from all their iniquities, whereby they have ſinned againſt mee.</hi> Now when thou goeſt about that duty required, and findeſt thy ſelfe unable, then looke to that ſame promiſe; And in the apprehenſion thereof, thy ſoule ſhall looke up, and goe about the worke in the ſtrength (not of thy ſelfe) but of the mighty God of grace, who hath ſpoken, and will doe it for thee. So for Repentance, He commands thee to <hi>repent. Acts</hi> 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. Thou goeſt about it, but findeſt the worke of Repentance <hi>(true and unfayned)</hi> too hard for thee to performe: Then turne from this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165154:11"/>precept to that promiſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. And when thou there ſeeſt, that hee that hath commanded thee to repent, even the God of power, and truth, and that cannot lye, hath engaged himſelfe to enable thee to the performance thereof, wilt thou not bee encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged?</p>
            <p>Againe, He commands thee, <hi>not to let ſin reigne in thee,</hi> Rom. 6.12. And is not the promiſe nigh thee (ver. 14.) <hi>that it ſhall not reigne in thee</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Thou wilt ſay, Theſe promiſes indeed are made to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and to Saints!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let that bee granted: Yet art thou excluded? Canſt thou ſay thou art not elected? How wilt thou prove it? wilt thou dive into the ſecret Counſell of God? It is too deepe for thee to fathome. Doeſt thou complain that thy wicked life doth evidence it? Well; Conſider then: haſt thou denyed Chriſt? So did <hi>Peter,</hi> haſt thou perſecuted Chriſt? did not <hi>Paul</hi> ſo? And yet for all this, were not they elected? In a word; There is not a man or woman under the whole Heavens can juſtly or truly ſay, he or ſhee is not elected, of this many reaſons and teſtimonies might be given, but I would not be tedious.</p>
            <p>Hee commands thee to love him, with all thy heart with all thy ſtrength and with all thy ſoul, <hi>Deu.</hi> 10.12. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. The Lord comes in with his promiſe, ſaying. <hi>I wil circumciſe thine heart, and the heart of thy ſeed, to love the lord thy God, with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule, that thou mayeſt live.</hi> He commands Col. 3 5. <hi>To mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie thy earthly members which are upon the earth &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Micah</hi> 7 19. he undertakes the worke: <hi>Hee will ſubdue our iniquities, and caſt all our ſins into the depth of the Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.2. The Lord ſaith by <hi>Paul, Thou muſt keepe in memory, what is preached unto thee.</hi> But thou wilt ſay (as moſt doe) thou canſt not remember; then have recourſe to that promiſe, <hi>John</hi> 14 26. There the Lord undertakes and promiſeth to thee, ſaying, <hi>Hee will teach thee all things, and bring all things to thy remembrance, whatſoever he hath ſaid unto thee.</hi> So <hi>David Pſal</hi> 25 5. intreates the Lord to teach him, and inſtruct him in his way. And in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.12. The Lord undertakes the worke, and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.8. The Lord ſaith to him, <hi>I will inſtruct thee and teach thee in the way which thou ſhalt goe; I will guide thee with mine eye.</hi> And ſo for all things whatſoever the Lord thy God requireth of thee in any Scripture; In the ſame or another Scripture hee comes in with his ſweet, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165154:11"/>bleſſed promiſes of aſſiſtance, to enable thee unto it: He knows right well as ſaith <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> chap. 10.23. <hi>Ehe way of man is not in himſelfe, it is not in man that walketh to direct his ſteps.</hi> In a word, conſider; There bee many of the greateſt promiſes amidſt the greateſt precepts. So <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.20. Hee commands thee to feare him, and <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39. Hee comes with a ſweet promiſe ſaying, <hi>I will give thee an heart to feare mee,</hi> and in another Scripture. <hi>I will put my feare into your hearts.</hi> Truly friend, the conſideration of this, will ſweeten all the commands of the Lord unto thee, and it will cauſe thee to ſet about what is required, in the ſtrength (not of thy ſelfe) but of the Lord, then goe on, and bee ſtrong in him and in the power of his might. Now to draw to a concluſion, conſider theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That if after all theſe ſweete encouragements, invitations, entreatings, perſwaſions, beſeechings, thou continue ſtill in unbeliefe, and will not come to him that thou mayeſt have life, although hee doth proteſt that him, that doth come to him, hee will in no wiſe caſt out, <hi>John</hi> 6.37. It is the greateſt of thy ſinnes, and it may be, thou ſhalt heare the Lords voyce changed and telling thee, <hi>the axe is laid to the root of the tree, and hee that brings not forth good fruit ſhall be hewen downe and caſt into the fire:</hi> Or ſuppoſe thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt heare him ſaying to thee as once he was to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Mat. 23.37. <hi>Oh Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, how often would I have gathered thy children together even as a Hen gathereth her Chickens, but yee would not: Behold your houſe is left unto you deſolate.</hi> Prov. 1.24. 25. <hi>Becauſe I have called and yee refuſed, I have ſtretched out my ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and no man regarded,</hi> verſe 26. <hi>I alſo will laugh at your cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and mocke when your feare commeth.</hi> Reade and well conſider that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.16, 17. <hi>Eſau</hi> having ſlighted and undervalued his birth-right, would afterwards have repented, but could not, though hee ſought it with teares. <hi>Therefore to day if you will heare his voyce harden not your hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider; The day is at hand, in which all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the world, all the Tribes, Kindreds and Tongues under the heavens that now are, ever were or ſhall be, I ſay all, both ſmall and great ſhall be gathered together before the judgement Seat of Chriſt. <hi>Math.</hi> 25.32.33, 34. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea the Sea ſhall give up her dead, and the Grave ſhall give up her dead: Death and Hell ſhall give up their dead. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12, 13, 14. In another place wee reade, that we ſhall all appeare before the judgement Seat of Chriſt, and all that ever thou haſt done, good, or evill, ſhall be laid open before all the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165154:12"/>world, all thy ſins, ſecret and open, ſhall be brought to light; and thou ſhalt bee judged according to thy workes, <hi>Math.</hi> 25.32, 33, 34, 35. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12, 13. Then when the ſecrets of all hearts are laid open, if thou art found a beleever in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and that thou haſt made him thy confidence, then thou ſhalt in that terrible day ſtand up with boldneſſe, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.17. And thy Judge (which is thy Saviour) ſhall ſay to thee, as in <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34. <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father, inherit yee the Kingdome prepared for you, from the foundation of the world,</hi> then ſhall all teares bee wiped from thine eyes, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flye away, there ſhall bee eaſe without payne, beauty without blemiſh, credit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſgrace, in a word, thy priviledges and enjoyments ſhall be ſo great, as the heart of man cannot conceive, much leſſe his tongue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port: for thou ſhalt be like him. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p>But if thy name be not writen in the Lambs book, if thou conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueſt ſtill in unbelief, and endeſt thy days with an evill life: Oh what a terrible day will this be unto thee! 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12. The heavens ſhall be on fire and diſſolve; the earth alſo it ſhall melt with fervent heat: then, if the rocks and mountains might fall on thee, thou wouldeſt think it a favour, to hide thee from the face of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lambe; for the great day of his wrath is come: and who ſhall abide it? <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.16, 17, &amp;c. Then ſhalt thou hear that dreadfull ſentence paſſe on thee, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.41. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me yee Curſed into Everlaſting fire, prepared for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and his Angels.</hi> Conſider a little, this dolefull ſentence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thou muſt depart from the preſence of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thou departeſt (not bleſſed but) a curſed wretch. <hi>Depart from me yee curſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Not onely into fire, but into everlaſting fire, no hope of retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The companions that thou ſhalt have there, are the Devill and his Angels, <hi>Depart from me yee curſed into everlaſting fire, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the Devill and his Angels.</hi> And this dreadfull day will come as a thiefe in the night, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. <hi>In which the heavens ſhall paſſe away with a great noiſe, and the element ſhall melt with fervent heat, and the earth alſo and the works that are therein, ſhall be burnt up,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Seeing then that all theſe things ſhall be diſſolved.</hi> 2 Pet. 3.11. <hi>What manner of perſons ought you to be, in all holy converſation and godlineſſe? Oh!</hi> then take heed, <hi>Watch and pray, for you know not how near the time is.</hi> Mark 13.33. <hi>The day of the Lord commeth as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165154:12"/>a thiefe in the night,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.2. <hi>Wherefore (beloved) ſeeing that you look for ſuch things, be diligent that you may be found of him in peace, without ſpot and blameleſſe,</hi> 2. Pet. 3.14.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider, if it ſhould be a few moneths or years before this great and terrible day come; yet it may not, for ought that thou knoweſt, be many dayes, no, not ſo much as many houres or minutes, before thy particular end come; in which, thou ſhalt be gaſping for life, and breathing out thy laſt breath: If then thou look up, God will appear as an angry Judge; if thou look down, the bottomleſſe Pit will ſtrike terrour into thee; on thy right hand, thy ſins ſtand accuſing thee; on thy left hand, the Devill is ready to execute Gods eternall ſentence upon thee; within thee, thy conſcience gnawing; without thee, thy friends bewailing. So that look which way thou wilt, above thee, beneath thee, within thee, without thee; every ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject will adde to thy miſerie. Therefore, <hi>Oh, remember thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, before theſe evill daies come</hi> Eccleſ. 12.1. Intreat the Lord, as <hi>David</hi> did, Pſal. 39.4. <hi>Lord make mee to know mine end, and the meaſure of my daies, what it is; That I may know how fraile I am.</hi> And wilt thou know how fraile thou art, oh vaine man? then conſider,</p>
            <p>One ſcripture ſaith of thy dayes, it is as water ſpilt upon the ground, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.14. Another ſcripture ſaith, <hi>Our dayes are like a ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</hi> Pſal. 102.11. And as if that were too long, <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, Job 7.7, <hi>My life is but a winde:</hi> Pſal. 102.3. <hi>Our daies conſume like ſmoak. Wee all doe fade as a leafe,</hi> Iſa. 64 6. <hi>All fleſh is graſſe, and all the glory of man, as the flower of the graſſe, the graſſe withereth, and the flower thereof falleth away.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.24. And as if all theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances ſignified too much length, to hold forth the ſhortnes of our life; the holy Ghoſt doth contract it ſhorter. Pſal. 39 5. <hi>Thou haſt made my dayes as an hand breadth.</hi> And as if that reſemblance alſo, were too long, he ſaith in the ſame verſe, <hi>Mine age is as nothing.</hi> Well then doth the ſcripture in many places ſay, <hi>We are like a buble of the brooke, a tale that is told, or a dream.</hi> Oh how ſhould the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration hereof, teach thee ſo <hi>to number thy dayes, that thou mighteſt apply thine heart to true and perfect wiſdome.</hi> Or as the wiſe man ſaith, Eccleſ. 12.6. <hi>Remember thy creator before the ſilver cord be looſed, or the golden bowle be broken,</hi> for as death leaves thee, ſo Judgement will finde thee, &amp;c. In a word, it is a point of high wiſdome, to be often thinking and meditating of out latter end, for the Lord himſelf faith, Deut. 32.29. <hi>That they were wiſe, that they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165154:13"/>underſtood this, to conſider their latter end.</hi> So he that made thee, teach and perfect thee.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Two Words to thoſe choſen out of the World.</head>
               <p>NOw I ſhall come to ſpeak two words to thoſe that are choſen out of the World.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Generally, to all the Saints.</p>
               <p>Secondly, More particularly, to the Saints under thoſe titles, or forms, by which they are moſt commonly known.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The word in generall. To all that are truly godly, for now to you I ſpeak, <hi>even to you my fellow members, and brethren in Chriſt.</hi> Awake, awake, Put on t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſtrength O <hi>Sion,</hi> put on thy beautifull garments, O <hi>Ieruſalem, thou holy City.</hi> Iſa. 52.1. <hi>Ariſe my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and come away,</hi> 2 Can. 10.13. <hi>For the day is dawning, and the day-ſtar ariſing in your hearts,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.19.</p>
               <p>Oh Saints! Conſider a little upon what ground you ſtand, upon what foundation you are built: doeſt thou believe there was ſuch a Chriſt as the ſcriptures mention? Doeſt thou believe that this Chriſt took thy nature, and alſo thy ſins? Doeſt thou believe, that in this thy nature, he fulfilled the law, took it away, nailed it to the Croſſe, and ſo is become the end of the law to all that believe? alſo freed thee from ſin paſt, preſent, and to come, and ſo from death the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges thereof? doeſt thou conceive; that God will make good his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes, in particular theſe? Iſa. 25.7, 8, <hi>&amp;c. He will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy in this mountain, the face of the covering caſt over all people, and the vaile that is ſpread over all nations, He will ſwallow up death in victory: And the Lord God will wipe away tears from of all faces, And the rebuke of his people ſhall bee taken away, from off all the earth.</hi> Doeſt thou believe that the knowledge of the Lord ſhall cover the earth as the waters the Sea, and that <hi>We ſhall all know him from the greateſt to the leaſt.</hi> Jer. 31.34. Doeſt thou believe thoſe words, which the Lord ſpake to <hi>Daniel,</hi> chap. 7.27. <hi>And the kingdome, and the dominion, and the greatnes of the kingdome under the whole heavens</hi> (mark this word <hi>under the whole heavens</hi>) <hi>ſhall be given to the people of the Saints, for their kingdome is an everlaſting king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and all dominions, ſhall ſerve and obey them.</hi> Doeſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thoſe words, Iſa. 30.26. <hi>Moreover the light of the Moone ſhall be as the light of the Sun, and the light of the Sun ſhall be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venfold?</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:165154:13"/>Doeſt thou believe, <hi>that the Lord will wipe away all tears from off all faces, and that there ſhall be no more ſorrow nor crying: neither ſhall there be any more pain.</hi> Revel. 21.4. Doeſt thou believe what the Lord ſaith, in Iſa. 35.10. <hi>And the ranſomed of the Lord ſhall return, and come to</hi> Sion, <hi>with ſongs, and everlaſting joy, upon their heads; They ſhall obtain joy and gladnes; and ſorrows and ſighing ſhall flie away.</hi> Doeſt thou believe the Lord will heal all our back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings, all our diſtractions? and compoſe all our differences? and give all his people one heart and one way? <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39. Read under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandingly, that 11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.7, 8, 9 <hi>The Woolfe alſo ſhaell dwell with the Lambe, and the Leopard ſhall lie down with the Kid, and the Calf, and the young Lion, and the fatling together; and the Cow, and the Beare ſhall feed their young, and lie down together. And the Lion, ſhall eate ſtraw like the Oxe, and the ſucking childe ſhall play on the hole of the Aſpe, and the weaned childe ſhall put his hand on the Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>katrice den. They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all mine holy mountain, for the earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea. Light is ſown for the righteous; and gladnes for the upright in heart. Iſa.</hi> 79 11.12. Therefore rejoyce in the Lord yee righteous and give thanks at the remembrance of his holines. Theſe (and, many ſcriptures more, which for brevity I omit) doe ſhew thee, ô moſt noble overcomming Saint, that glorious times are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; wherefore, <hi>gird up the loins of thy minde, be ſober, and hope to the end,</hi> for the grace that is to be brought unto thee, at the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. And when he is revealed; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many mercies, which thou ſhalt receive, I will onely mention two.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he ſhall appear without ſin; and thou ſhalt appear ſo in him <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9 the laſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Thou ſhalt be like him; for thou ſhalt ſee him, as he is. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then when thy ſoule apprehends this, it will even break forth into praiſes, and ſongs of deliverance, as once <hi>David:</hi> God let in a light, whereby he ſaw his ſins pardoned. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Bleſſe the Lord O my ſoul, and all that is within me, bleſſe his holy name. Bleſſe the Lord O my ſoule and forget not all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits. Who forgiveth all thine iniquities, who healeth all thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. Who redeemeth thy life from death, who crowneth thee with loving kindnes, and tender mercies.</hi> If thou ask, why I doe ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſo many ſcriptures, and not explain them, I anſwer. Remember to whom I ſpeak, that is, to the choſen generation, to the Saints enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165154:14"/>and they have the ſum of them opened to them already; or at reaſt they have the ſpirit of God in them, which is the trueſt Key to unfold, or unlock the myſterie of them, unto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2. But I ſuppoſe; that many of theſe forementioned pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes were made unto particular Saints, as, to the Jews, or the like; And ſo have been fulfilled to them: And if ſo, Then what matter of comfort can they adminiſter unto me?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer</hi> Suppoſe it were ſo; That they bee fulfilled already: (which I know, moſt doe ſay) yet in ſome meaſure (through Gods goodnes) I doe know the contrary; they are wholly, or for the greateſt part, yet to be fulfilled: as I could prove by ſcripture; but I forbear becauſe I would not be tedious. But ſuppoſe they were made to ſome particular Saints, and fulfilled to them, yet they are in whole, or in part, appliable to thee, as to inſtance in one ſcripture for all. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.5. The Lord promiſed <hi>Joſhua, that he would never leave him nor forſake him.</hi> And the Apoſtle in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. preſſeth the Saints to make uſe of, and to lay hold on that promiſe, as made to <hi>them,</hi> though it was made to <hi>Joſhua</hi> many hundred yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 3. If they be yet to bee fulfilled, it is a great queſtion whether I ſhall live to ſee any of them fulfilled, and then what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort doe they hold forth to mee?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If thou doeſt not live to ſee them fulfilled with thy bodily eyes, yet with the eye of Faith, which is the evidence of things not ſeen (<hi>with naturall eyes</hi>) Heb. 11.1. Thou mayeſt ſee them fulfilled to <hi>thee:</hi> as the Saints Hebr. 11.13. <hi>They all dyed in the Faith, not having received the promiſes, but having ſeen them a farre off,</hi> and were perſwaded of them, and embraced them, that is, They lived in the enjoyment of them, in the Spirit. Again, 1 <hi>Theſſ</hi> 4.16.17. There are promiſes made; one, <hi>That the dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt,</hi> and another, <hi>That we ſhall ever be with the Lord.</hi> And in the 18. verſ. He commands the Saints, that <hi>they ſhould comfort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with theſe words.</hi> Then (in one word) this is the ſumme to be learned from hence; that we ſhould not onely rejoyce in the preſent enjoyments, but live in a full expectation of (and comfort in) what wee ſhall ſhortly enjoy; <hi>and comfort one another with theſe words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is not that time drawing neare which is propheſied of, Rev. 11.15. <hi>And the ſeventh Angel ſounded, and there were great voyces in Heaven, ſaying, the Kingdomes of this world are become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:165154:14"/>of our Lord, and of his Sonne Chriſt, and hee ſhall reigne for evermore.</hi> Wherefore, moſt noble over-comming Saints, Servants of the moſt high, and mighty God, looke for great alterations, and mighty changes. See what deſolations God will make in the earth, when he hath accompliſhed his worke upon mount Sion, then hee will Judge the Mountaine of <hi>Eſau;</hi> that is, when God hath fully brought up his people to enjoy nothing but himſelfe, then he will declare himſelfe to be a God taking vengeance, on his, and our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Wherefore rejoyce O you Saints, for the time of your ſinging is come. The day of our redemption is appearing. Howle oh <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon:</hi> Mourne oh thou proud oppoſer of Chriſt, thy pride is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, thy end is comming: Who will mourne for thee? Then ſhall all thy lovers ſtand a farre off, for feare of thy torments; they ſtand farre off, they will not come neare to comfort thee. Bee ſilent then, oh all fleſh, for the Lord is riſen out of his holy habitation. Then wilt thou break forth as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.9. And it ſhall be ſaid in that day, <hi>This is our God; wee have waited for him: This is our Lord; wee have waited for him; we will bee glad and rejoyce in his ſalvation.</hi> Then by this glorious appearing hee will deſtroy the face of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering caſt over all people, and the vaile that is ſpread over all nations, and hee will ſwallow up death in victory, and the Lord God will wipe away teares, from off all faces, and the rebuke of his people ſhall be taken away, from off all the earth: for the Lord hath ſpoken it. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.7, 8. Oh Saints, lift up your heads, your redemption draws nigh; and now will our God make good to us, that which is written. Zephe. 3.9. <hi>I will turne to the people of pure Language, and they ſhall ſerve me, with one conſent.</hi> This pure Language is the Language of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Is appointed by God to put an end to theſe diviſions, not till then ſhall the envy of <hi>Ephraim</hi> depart, and the enemies of <hi>Judah</hi> be cut off, <hi>Ephraim</hi> not envy <hi>Judah,</hi> nor <hi>Judah</hi> vexe <hi>Ephraim.</hi> Then the Kingdome, and the dominion, and the greatneſſe of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſhall bee given to the Kingdome of the Saints; <hi>Whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is an ever laſting Kingdome, and all dominions ſhall ſerve and obey them,</hi> Dan. 7.27. <hi>Then the Nations that will not ſerve thee</hi> (that is Chriſt in the Saints) <hi>ſhall periſh</hi> Iſa. 60.12 Now God, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given you all one heart, and one way, as it is written <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.19 Now ſhall bee brought to paſſe that ſaying, Iſa. 11.6, 7, 8. <hi>The Woolfe ſhall dwell with the Lambe, and the Leopard ſhall lye downe with the Kid</hi> &amp;c. verſe 9. <hi>They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:165154:15"/>mine holy mountaine, for the Earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea. The envy of</hi> Ephraim <hi>ſhall depart, and the Adverſaries of</hi> Judah <hi>ſhall be cut off: Then all you, the</hi> Iſraell <hi>of God, ſhall have your Fathers law written in your hearts.</hi> Then you ſhall ceaſe, <hi>teaching one another, ſaying, know the Lord, for they ſhall all of them know mee, from the leaſt to the greateſt of them, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 31.34</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My deare friends,</hi> I have much more to write unto you of theſe things, but being more ſtraitned in time, than in love; at preſent, I ſhall paſſe by many things, firſt concerning the reſtitution of all things ſpoken of <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19, 20, 21, 22, 23. and <hi>Acts</hi> 3 20, 21, 22, 23, 24. And to in many other Scriptures, which for preſent I omit, and then, what ſhall follow upon the reſtitution of all things <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2, 3, 4. Theſe things were in my heart, to write of diſtinctly, ſeeing that all, as well Saints as ſinners are extreamely ignorant of theſe tnings, though moſt clearly held forth in Scripture, that a man can hardly ſpeake of them, though he ſpeaks no more than the Hiſtory holds forth, but one is offended and another is troubled, therefore at preſent I am ſilent therein: As our Lord ſaid, I have more things to ſpeake, but yee cannot beare them now; and this Scripture likewiſe, <hi>Haſt thou faith? have it to thy ſelfe</hi> &amp;c. So I paſſe by that which thou ſhalt ſhortly enjoy, and come to ſpeake a few words of what many of the Saints doe already enjoy, and oh that all the Saints did but truly conſider theſe enſuing things, which I never received of man, neither was I taught them by man: but of God alone.</p>
               <p>Thou that art a beleever, conſider;</p>
               <p>Firſt, The law that thou haſt broken, Chriſt hath kept, fulfilled, and taken away.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Thy ſinnes which were many, both originall, and actuall, of omiſſion, and commiſſion, thy ſins paſt, thoſe preſent, and thoſe to come, are all laid upon Chriſt, and the wages due to them heereceived.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Conſider, Upon what accompt thou now ſtandeſt, before the Father, not of thine owne righteouſneſſe but the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Conſider, That thou being made free from ſin, doeſt reckon thy ſelfe ſo, Rom. 6.11. <hi>Likewiſe reckon your ſelves to be dead indeed unto ſin, but alive unto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, When thou art thus built upon Chriſt; and thus rooted,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:165154:15"/>and grounded in him, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.18, 19. Then thou ſhalt be able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend with all Saints, what is the height, and depth, breadth, and length of his love, and to know the love of Chriſt, which paſſeth knowledge.</p>
               <p>Now followes, the fruit of this knowledge; The ſoule that is enlightened, will not goe on in ſinne, but the love of Chriſt will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine him from a courſe of ſinne, I ſhall ſpeake a word to every one of theſe particulars, briefly, and plainely.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of the firſt, the Law, that thou haſt broken, <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath kept, fulfilled, and taken away. The Law required obedience of thee, Chriſt comes, and yeelds obedience for thee, and imputes it to thee, Rom. 5.19. <hi>As by the diſobedience of one, many are made ſinners; ſo by the obedience of one, ſhall many bee made righteous.</hi> The Law required the keeping of every title, of the firſt and ſecond Table, Chriſt comes and walkes up to it, ſtep by ſtep. So that the Law could no ſooner require obedience, but preſently Chriſt yeelds obedience, as it was in the old Teſtament propheſied, and in the new, teſtified of him. The Law required an holy life; Chriſt lived a holy life: The Law required perfect obedience, as well in the principles, as in the practiſe; Chriſt yeelds it in both: The Law requires death for the leaſt diſobedience, and though Chriſt had not broken it in any title, yet hee repreſenting the perſons of thoſe that had broken it, became obedient unto the Law in this alſo, Phillip. 2.8. <hi>And being found in faſhion as a man, he humbled himſelfe, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the Croſſe:</hi> And that the Law is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by Chriſt ſee 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. foure times in that chapter it is ſaid to bee done away. Alſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4. and ſo the 2, 3, 4. chap. to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> and many other Scriptures.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider, Thy ſinnes which are many, both originall, and actuall, of omiſſion, or commiſſion, againſt the firſt Table, or the ſecond, thy ſins, paſt, preſent and to come, are all laid upon Chriſt, and the wages due to them hee received, Iſai. 53 6. <hi>And the Lord hath laid on him, the iniquities of us all:</hi> 1 Pet. 2.24. <hi>Who himſelfe, bare our ſins in his owne body, on the tree,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Cor. 5.21. <hi>Hee hath made him to be ſin for us, that knew no ſin, that we might bee made the righteouſneſſe of God in him,</hi> Mat, 8.17. <hi>Himſelfe tooke our infirmities, and bare our ſickneſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider, Upon what accompt you ſtand before the Father, <hi>viz.</hi> not of your own righteouſne, but upon the accompt of the righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt. 1 Cor. 1.30. <hi>Hee is made unto us,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:165154:16"/>wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, and redemption.</hi> Phil. 3.9. <hi>And be found in him, not having mine owne righteouſneſſe, which is of the Law, but that which is through the Faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe of God by Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſider, If the Law be fulfilled, thy ſinnes pardoned, and thou now ſtandeſt before thy Father, by the righteouſneſſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Then thou canſt not but looke upon thy ſelfe as free from ſin, and ſo breake forth, as in Rom. 6.11. <hi>Likewiſe, reckon your ſelves dead unto ſinne indeed, but alive unto God. Being then made free from ſinne, yee became the Servants of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> Rom. 6.18, <hi>But now being made free from ſin, and become Servants to God, yee have your fruit unto holineſſe, and the end everlaſting life,</hi> Rom 6.22 Collo. 1.22. <hi>Hee hath reconciled you in the body of his fleſh through death, to preſent you holy, and unblameable, and unreprovable in his ſight,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 3.13. Now one that is, 1. Holy, 2. Unblameable, 3. Unreproveable, muſt needs be free from ſin.</p>
               <p n="5">5. When thou art thus rooted and grounded in love, thou ſhalt be able to comprehend with all Saints, <hi>What is the breadth, and length, and height, and depth, and to know the love of Chriſt, which paſſeth knowledge,</hi> Ephe. 3.18. <hi>So ſhalt thou be filled with all the fulneſſe of God,</hi> verſe 19. My thinks I ſee many of the Saints, even breaking forth in the language of <hi>Mary,</hi> Luke 46, 47.48. <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie the Lord, my Spirit doth rejoyce in God my Saviour,</hi> (and then gives occaſion of this Joy) <hi>for he hath regarded the low eſtate of his hand-maid.</hi> The tongue of the dumbe doth begin to ſing, the eyes of the blind to be opened, and the eares of the deafe to heare. Reade the 35. of <hi>Iſaiah:</hi> that whole chapter, briefly and plainly layes downe, by way of propheſie; that he, our tender father, is bringing downe the mighty from their ſeat, and exalting them of low legree: yea, he rebuketh Kings for your ſakes; your God, is no reſpecter of perſons: If Kings and Princes rebell againſt him, and his choſen ones, hee will bring downe their heads as low as the block, and if theſe great ones endeavour to ſeperate God and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, God will ſeperate their heads from their bodies, you ſee theſe dayes of ours doe witneſſe to this; in a word, He is pulling downe the Kingdomes of men, and ſetting up the Kingdome of his deare Sonne. And how doth the brutiſh Malignant, rage, and the poor blind Presbyterian murmure, at the going on of Gods worke, let mee ſay to both as Prov. 1.22. <hi>How long you ſimple ones, will you love ſimplicity?</hi> What; doe you not know that God, hath an attribute
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:165154:16"/>of juſtice, that he will magnifie, as well as that of his mercy. If he afflict his own dear children whom he ſo loves, will he not execute vengeance on his adverſaries? Be ſilent then all fleſh before him, for the Lord will bring to paſſe his work; yea his ſtrange work. True Juſtice hath no reſpect of perſons: wherefore turn your murmuring, and repining, into rejoycing, and thankſgiving for the juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, upon the enemies of his truth. O you moſt noble overcomming Saints, ſervants, of the moſt high God, you ſhall judge Angels as well as earthly Kings. Your Father loves you, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will honour you, (nay, he doth honour thee already.) <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that honour me I will honour,</hi> ſaith the Lord. Firſt,</p>
               <p n="1">1. He cals thee his ſervant, and that is a great honour, to be a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to ſo heavenly a Prince, but, as if that were too little.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He cals you his choſen ones, his friends, <hi>Joh</hi> 15.15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He cals you his brethren and ſiſters. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He cals you his ſonnes and daughters, a more near relation, yet as if that were a ſtile too low to expreſſe his tender love unto you.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He cals you his choſen Spouſe, and Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9.</p>
               <p n="6">6. He cals you members of his own body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Hee tels you, yee are coheires with himſelf, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</p>
               <p n="8">8. He tels you, that the glory that the Father gave to him, he hath given to you; that you may be one, as the Father and he are one.</p>
               <p n="9">9. He tels you, that you are not onely one in the body; but one in the ſpirit alſo. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And laſtly, He tels you that this is but a ſhort taſte of what you ſhall be, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1.2.</p>
               <p>How will the conſideration of theſe near relations cauſe you to break forth with the holy Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.17. <hi>As he is ſo are we in this preſent world,</hi> Or as in <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11. Both he that ſanctifieth, and they that are ſanctified are all one: again, Hence it is, that the Lord ſaith, <hi>He that toucheth them, toucheth the apple of mine eye:</hi> In a word, the Lord takes all the wrongs done to any of his, as done to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou mee? I was an hungred, and yee gave me no meat: I was thirſty, and you gave me no drink. I was a ſtranger, and you took me not in: naked, and yee cloathed me not. Sick, and in Priſon, and you viſited me not: In aſmuch as you did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, you did it not to mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, conſider, As thy moſt wiſe God, turns all things to his own glory; ſo likewiſe he turns them to thy good: To inſtance in a few
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:165154:17"/>things, as firſt; The very fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> wherein the Devill thought to have wrought thy ruine, God in his wiſdome hath turned it to thy greateſt good. And in the ſame thing, wherein the Devill thought to caſt thee, thy God appointed to recover thee: <hi>Adam</hi> fell through unbelief; thou rifeſt again by Faith; and the ſtate in which thou ſtandeſt in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> is a more firme and glorious ſtate than that of the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi> So that thou haſt gotten many priviledges by his fall: For inſtance,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Adam,</hi> though made without ſin, yet might ſin. Now it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for thee, as thou art made a new creature by Chriſt, to ſin. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.6, 9</p>
               <p n="2">2. The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was made inferiour to Angels, but the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> hath made thee equall with (if not above) the Angels <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.36. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22 30.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had power over viſible creatures of the earth; but thou (being reſtored by the ſecond<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Adam</hi>) haſt power over principalities, and ſpirituall wickedneſſes in high places. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Adam</hi> was made righteous, and that was a glorious ſtate, but the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> hath made thee <hi>the righteouſnes of God in him.</hi> 2 Corin. 5. verſ. 21.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> in his beſt eſtate, was ſubject to fall by the temptation of evil Angels. But nothing can make a ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thee and thy God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Adam</hi> had but a temporall paradiſe, at the beſt; but the ſonnes of <hi>Sion</hi> by virtue of their ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> have a ſpirituall Paradiſe. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23.</p>
               <p>Oh, the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and knowledgeoff God, <hi>how unſearchable are his judgements, and his wayes paſt finding out.</hi> Well doth <hi>John</hi> ſay, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.36. <hi>Hee that believeth on the ſoune, hath everlaſting life,</hi> mark: he doth not ſay he <hi>ſhall</hi> have everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life; but he <hi>hath</hi> it already. And particularly he hath it thus,</p>
               <p n="1">1. He hath everlaſting life in the <hi>promiſe; Feare not little flock: it is your fathers good pleaſure to give you the Kingdome</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. He hath it in the firſt fruits: for what is heaven, but a more full enjoyment hereafter of what is begun here?</p>
               <p n="3">3. He hath it <hi>even now</hi> in poſſeſſion, by Chriſt his head; for Chriſt his head is entred in already. Oh then you ſervants of God! If you be entred into heaven, if you have received a kingdome that cannot be moved, <hi>Serve God acceptably with reverence and godly fear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:165154:17"/>So having ſpoken a word in generall, to all the ſons of <hi>Zion;</hi> give me leave to ſpeak a word in particular to each of them under their ſeverall forms, and herein, I ſhall ſomwhat differ from the practice of moſt men.</p>
               <p>I ſhall firſt take notice of thoſe things that are commendable in the Saints, to whom I write; to cheriſh and commend that. And</p>
               <p>Secondly, Reprove them ſharpely (but yet in the Spirit of love and meeknes) for the evill among them. So did <hi>Paul</hi> with the Church of <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1 <hi>Corin.</hi> 1.4. and ſo to the 15. verſe. So dealt Chriſt with the Church of <hi>Epheſus Rev</hi> 2. from the firſt ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe to the end of the fift. And in the ſame manner he ſpake to the Church of <hi>Pergamus, Revel</hi> 2. from the 12. verſe to the end of the 16. And ſo when he wrote to the Church of <hi>Thyatira, Revel.</hi> 2.18, 19. <hi>I know thy works, and charitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſervice, and faith, and thy patience; and how thou groweſt, for thy laſt works be more than thy firſt.</hi> So having taken notice of the things commendable, and praiſed them for that, <hi>verſe</hi> 20. in the next place (not the firſt) he reproves their evill, ſaying, <hi>Nevertheleſſe I have a few things againſt thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this order or method, I ſhall at preſent ſpeak; not in oppoſition to, or deniall of any way now in practice amongſt the godly, and warranted by the Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Word to thoſe that have taken to themſelves the name of <hi>PRESBYTERIANS.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Brethren,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY hearts deſire and prayer to God is, that the God of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Father of glory may give unto each of you the Spirit of Wiſdome and Revelation, in the knowledge of him: That you may be able to comprehend, with all Saints, what is the breadth and length, and height, &amp; depth, &amp; to know the love of Chriſt, which paſſeth knowledge, that you might be filled with all the fulneſſe of God; I thank my God on your behalf, for the grace of God that is in ſome meaſure given to many of you already, by Jeſus Chriſt. God hath made ſome of you inſtrumentall, for the converſion of ſouls, by the preaching of his Word. And I my ſelf, muſt acknowledge to the glory of God, and to your praiſe; that I have had many ſweet and heavenly refreſhments by your teachings, and ſolid diſcourſes, both in publique and private. In ſome things God hath enlightened me
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:165154:18"/>by you; and in ſome other things, I have been convinced by you; and in ſome other things, I have been confirmed by you: Theſe things I ſpeak by experience; and beſides, I have heard from ſome others, that they have alſo received the like benefits from the Lord by you. Again, Many of you are men of tender conſciences, In ſo much that when you ſee but the very appearance of evill, you will abſtain from it. And the Charitie of many of you to the Poore is very large, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the relation of many poore Souls, whoſe bowels you have refreſhed; and appears alſo by your ſtirring up others, to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that duty.</p>
               <p>By my Brethren! there are faults amongſt <hi>you:</hi> therefore I have a few things againſt you.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Why do you ſo frequently complain againſt this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Army, ſaying; they be pulling down Magiſtracy and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry? are they pulling down any ſuch Magiſtracy or Miniſtry, as Chriſt hath ſet up? Or elſe ſuch as Anti-chriſt hath ſet up, and acted his deſigns by? Let him that is ſpirituall judge: if you examine our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, by the word of Truth; you ſhall eaſily ſee, that they are not according to Chriſt, but to Anti-chriſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Touching the Magiſtrate, I appeal to your Conſciences; Hath he been the Magiſtrate of God, for good to thee, in countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them that do well; and puniſhing of evill doers, or rather: Hath he not continually, for a long time, puniſhed thoſe that doe well; and countenanced thoſe that do ill: Herein, I will appeal to the ſons of <hi>Sion</hi> to judge: Have they not baniſhed, impriſoned, reproached, perſecuted, deſpiſed, and contemned, and that to the higheſt pitch of their power, all thoſe, in whom the fruits of the Spirit of Chriſt have appeared in any meaſure? And is this a lawfull authority which we ought to obey? Then let us never accompt it blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, to ſay, that the moſt wicked of actions are lawfull and juſt: For is any thing leſſe from the will of God, or more contrary to his commands, than this? Is not one unrighteouſnes as abſolute a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion as another?</p>
               <p>It is worth you pains to examin, what lawfull authority is? and let us conſider,</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>The powers that bee, are ordained of God.</hi> There is no power (that is lawfull) but it is of God; for this is moſt true, that the moſt high God is to reigne in the kingdome of men: and whoſoever are his inſtruments in governing, they muſt derive their power from him, and act purely <hi>the command of God, and no
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:165154:18"/>more, nor no leſſe, but even ſo;</hi> as it is recorded of the children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Exod. 39.42, 43. <hi>They had done the worke of the Tabernacle, as the Lord had commanded, even ſo they had done it. And</hi> (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it follows) Moſes <hi>bleſſed them.</hi> Wherefore were they bleſſed? Sure, you ſee, not for their own inventions, but for their obedience: ſo purely and exactly after the command of God. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be not the ſervants of men,</hi> that is; doe not you obſerve the things that men doe command, unleſſe God hath commanded them. But you will ask, How may we know the true power, from the falſe? <hi>Oh, that you were ſo teachable.</hi> Then</p>
               <p>The Scripture will tell you, that the lawfull powers are of God; both of his Commandements, and bearing his image, holy as he is holy; being a terrour not to good works, but to evill. And whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever doth reſiſt this power <hi>(onely this)</hi> he reſiſteth the Ordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance of God, and ſhall receive judgement to himſelf.</p>
               <p>But the Parliament and Army do not reſiſt this power (ſpoken of by <hi>Paul</hi> to be obeyed) But they doe reſiſt (and I admire that you the Seers doe not ſee it, that they do reſiſt) that power ſpoken of by <hi>Micha,</hi> Mic. 3.11. <hi>The heads thereof that doe judge for reward</hi> (and that <hi>eſtabliſh iniquity by a law</hi>) <hi>the Prieſts thereof that teach for hire, and the Prophets thereof</hi> that <hi>divine for money;</hi> and yet lean upon the Lord and ſay, <hi>is not the Lord amongſt us; No evill can come upon us.</hi> That the powers of this nation (that have been reſiſted) have been and are ſuch, their late actions are proofes, than which nothing can be more full or plaine, to men of reaſon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the Miniſtry, that are ſaid, to be pulling down: what are they? Apoſtles from Chriſt or from our Univerſities? who hath taught them? God or man? How are they conſtituted Miniſters? By God or man? a power internall or externall? By the hand and power of Gods Spirit upon their ſouls, and in them; or the hands of fleſh upon their heads of fleſh, without them? They faſt and pray for them; but is it therefore certain, that God doth hear and grant that particular thing? What is their principle? The Spirit and living power of God? Of the naturall and carnall Spirits of men? What is their knowledge? Of Faith, or of reaſon meerly humane? Is it of the Type, or Truth? Letter, or Spirit? Forme, or Power? have they received it by Revelation, or Tradition? And what is the end of moſt of them? Is it not worldly honour and power, earthly riches? will they preach if their profit invite them not? Doe they reckon themſelves rewarded, if they receive not money? Is not their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:165154:19"/>cry great, and their labour extream for Mammon, judge you. But theſe Miniſters are made ſuch, in a way of imitation: They ſay, they follow the pattern of the Apoſtles: But is it ſo? The Apoſtles had a glorious Spirit of light and power, poured out upon them; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily manifeſted in them, ſo that they were in a holy extaſie, ſeeming as men drunk, filled not with Wine, but the Spirit: that they plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaw the promiſes and propheſies fulfilled in them; and the world alſo might ſee, and ſay, that God was in them, becauſe of the works that were done by them. They profeſſed and declared, that they had not their doctrine of man, nor by man; but by God: they were not inſtructed through, or by means of the fleſhly Organs, or faculties of their bodies: or any fleſhly, or outward forme. But ſay they, the Goſpel of God is revealed in us, from Faith to Faith; the Spirit of God doth reveale it to us; we have taſted, and ſeen, and felt of the Word of Life. The things of God knows no man, but the Spirit of God; but we have the Spirit, &amp;c. And now are the pourings out of the Spirit upon all fleſh, heretofore propheſied and promiſed, &amp;c. By all which and other expreſſions of ſcripture, which are many and abundant; it is apparent that the Apoſtles had a miniſtration of light, life, power, and efficacie in them; which went forth by them in marveilous operations. Now they could with great boldnes and clearnes declare, and Preach the myſteries of the Goſpel; becauſe they had a clearneſſe of ſight of them, by a proper demonſtration and immediate manifeſtation, the Spirit of God dwelt in them, taught them plainly; and they certainly knew, that he taught them; they had ſure experience, as wee by our bodily ſight have experience or knowledge, that the Sun ſhineth.</p>
               <p>But amongſt all theſe pretenders to the miniſtry, and that appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate to themſelves that function, ſo diſtinct, as being the true and ſingular Apoſtle-imatators, or as if they were thereunto anointed and ſanctified above the reſt of Chriſtians, their brethren; where is he that God hath made ſo diſtinct by any guifts or endowments which either are comparable to thoſe of the primitive Chriſtians, or doe competently inable him to declare the myſtery of the Goſpel which as ſpirituall, ſo deepe and myſterious? Or wherein is he a Miniſter more than an ordinary Chriſtian? Nay I will be bold to ſay, that if they that are called the Miniſters, had but ſo much true light of the Goſpell revealed in them, as many private weake Children of God, it would cauſe them abſolutely to be aſhamed to be termed Miniſters, ſo unlike are they to and untruly counted ſuch. Can their humane
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:165154:19"/>wiſedome, their ſchoole-learning and arts, which are fleſh and of the world, unfold unto them the myſtery of Godlineſſe (ſo great?) If ſo, then the Apoſtle ſaid not truly, <hi>That God hath hid the things of his Spirit from the wiſe and prudent of the world, and revealed them to babes. And then alſo may the naturall man perceive the things of God,</hi> though <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith he cannot.</p>
               <p>And now if all your worldly and fleſhly wiſedome be no more to be accompted of, what then is your miniſtry? What is your complaint and murmuring againſt the Authority of the Nation? What are they pulling down, Apoſtles of Chriſt, or impoſters of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, Shepherds that feed the Sheep, or Wolves that devoure them; do they pull downe their feeders? or elſe their fleecers? Are they pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe leaders or ſeducers? May I not ſay to you in this caſe as our bleſſed Lord ſaid to <hi>Nicodemus</hi> in another caſe, John 3.10. <hi>Are you Maſters in Iſrael, and know not theſe things.</hi> Indeed they are pulling downe ſuch a miniſtry as is ſpoken of by the Prophet <hi>Micah,</hi> Micah 3.5. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, concerning the Prophets that make my people erre, that bite with their teeth, and yet cry peace, and he that putteth not into their mouths, they even prepare warre againſt him.</hi> And in the next verſe you may reade their judgement at large.</p>
               <p>Well then, will you be offended with Parliament and Army for pulling downe ſuch a magiſtracie and miniſtry, as this, let me beſeech you: Give over with ſpeed leaſt you fall with them.</p>
               <p>Againe; My friends: I doe admire that you complaine of the badneſſe of theſe times, ſurely you doe but dreame, for if you doe awake, you ſhall plainly ſee, that they are the beſt times with us in <hi>England,</hi> that ever we had, to live by faith, what? Hath the Lord with the Beſome of deſtruction ſwept away the head of the enemies of truth? And yet ſad times?</p>
               <p>What? Doth hee take Princes and Lords which were ſo high, and bring their Heads ſo low as the Blocke? And yet ſad times?</p>
               <p>What? Have the Saints in obedience to the command of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, given them to drink of the bitter, that they have given you ſo long? And yet ſad times?</p>
               <p>What? Is the Lord making inquiſition for blood; and meeting the ſame meaſure to his enemies, as they have meeted to his people? And yet ſad times? What? Is the Lord magnifying the attribute of his Juſtice, upon his and our implacable enemies? And yet ſad times?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:165154:20"/>What? Is the Lord pulling downe the powers of the world, and the Kingdomes of men, and ſetting up, or at leaſt making way to ſet up the Kingdome of his owne deare Son? And yet ſad times?</p>
               <p>Hath the Lord proſpered our Armies and given us ſo many Victories over them that would have devoured us? And yet ſad times?</p>
               <p>My Brethren: I am afraid you did not mourne with <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> becauſe you doe not now r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>joce with her. It is true, unto ſome, the times are ſad, but to whom?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To the deceivers of our nation, for theſe times doe diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, and (plainly) it is a bad time for falſe Prophets and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Judges, for God hath threatned their ruine, it is bad times for <hi>Babylon</hi> and all her brats, for the day of her deſtruction is dawning, and the houre of her plagues is comming when Kings and Princes, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Merchants, ſhall all lye howling, weeping and wailing, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>alas, alas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> And all the Saints ſhall ſtand before the preſence of their tender Father, <hi>ſinging, rejoycing and praiſing the Lord for his judgements upon their enemies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe; You Miniſters of the Presbiterian Congregations, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks you have loſt your beauty: I doe not ſee you in the affections of the Heires of promiſe, the Sonnes of Sion as formerly, the cauſe of this muſt be in the people or in your ſelves; and I have ſpent a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, and made diligent ſearch for to finde where the cauſe lyes, and have, with an impartiall heart, weighed the Saints in one bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance and you in another: And I finde <hi>you,</hi> not <hi>them,</hi> to light. I meane, I finde the cauſe of your being ſleighted to be in your ſelves, wherefore let me intreat you to take a word of advice from me, for, I aſſure you, I have taken adviſe from you, and (I hope) ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, though you looke upon me as onely worthy to be your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant or ſcholler, and not your teacher, yet I pray you, minde what <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>He will not deſpiſe the counſell of his Servant.</hi> And if you will indeed heare with your eares, treaſure up in your hearts, and practiſe in your lives theſe enſuing things, you ſhall ſoone grow in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour both with God and man.</p>
               <p>Then there be foure things that you muſt lay aſide and forſake, and there be five things that you muſt immediately doe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Lay aſide or leave of charging your hearers for breach of the <hi>Scotch Covenant,</hi> untill you have repented of your owne breach of that Covenant, for how can you preach, <hi>thou ſhalt not ſteale</hi> and ſteale your ſelves? How can you boldly reprove another for ſin, when
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:165154:20"/>you your ſelves are guilty of the ſame? How can you pull out th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moat that is in your brothers eye, untill you have pulled out th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beam, that is in your own eye. I will appeal to your very Conſcience then, whether you be not breakers of covenant in the higheſt nature: For ſaith the Covenant, <hi>You muſt bring to condigne puniſhment all delinquents:</hi> and you have often declared in the faces of your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, beſides, in your private diſcourſes, that the King was a delinquent in the higheſt nature: and yet almoſt all of you were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the bringing him to condigne puniſhment. Shall not many of the Army; which never took the Covenant; and yet had their hands in bringing malignants to puniſhment, riſe up in judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, which took a covenant to doe it; and yet above all men were againſt it; If this be not breach of Covenant, I do not know what is a breach.</p>
               <p>Again, you covenanted to endeavour in your places, the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion, according to the ſcriptures; but if you examine your Church-diſcipline by thoſe rules there held forth, and you ſhall ſee you have broken the Covenant in this alſo. And more I could ſhew you; but a word to the wiſe is enough: O my dear friends doe not you be like the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Iſaiah, Iſa.</hi> 28 7. <hi>They erre in viſion, they ſtumble in judgement;</hi> I ſay, do not you be like them in their ſin, leaſt the Lord make you like them in their puniſhment; and ſo ſpeak to his people as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.11. <hi>With a ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering lip and another tongue will he ſpeak to his people:</hi> and you that a little before were cryed up of many, as the onely Miniſters of the Goſpel, now are made like to thoſe propheſied of <hi>Micah,.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>Therefore night ſhall be unto you, that yee ſhall not have a viſion, and it ſhall be dark unto you, that yee ſhall not divine: and the Sun ſhall go over the Prophets, and the day ſhall be dark over them. Then ſhall the Seers be aſhamed, and the Diviners confounded: yea, they ſhall all cover their faces, for there is no anſwer of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Lay a ſide or leave off, that cold, lukewarm letter-preaching, which ſeems to be onely in the notion, received from tradition; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a form, but not the power: Remember how it was with <hi>Paul, he compared ſpirituall things with ſpirituall;</hi> and moſt of you (for I ſpeak not of all) compare letter with letter, and ſo come up with a voice of words, ſo cold, that ſome of your hearers begin to ſleep, and others to withdraw from your Congregations. Thoſe that doe indeed attend to what you ſpeak, are profitted very little by it. <hi>O come then, in the fulneſſe of the Goſpel of Chriſt; and as you have
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:165154:21"/>received the gift (not ſtudied) ſo adminiſter the ſame.</hi> See what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Rom. 15. v. 8. <hi>I will not dare to ſpeak of thoſe things which Chriſt hath not wrought in mee: to make the Gentiles obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient by word and deed.</hi> Again, 2 Cor. 10.15, 16. <hi>Wee will not (ſaith the Apoſtle) boaſt of things without our meaſure;</hi> that is, of other mens labours: <hi>Wee will preach the Goſpel, and not boaſt in another mans line;</hi> of things made ready to our hands. Let me then appeal to your conſciences, whether this be your practice. Again, <hi>Why do you tye your ſelves,</hi> to preach onely ſo long, and not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times longer, or ſhorter: did ever the Prophets or Apoſtles doe ſo? Why do you tye your ſelves, to ſpeak onely from one text, in one Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon? did ever the Prophets and Apoſtles tie themſelves conſtantly as you do your ſelves to this. But think not that I write againſt preaching an houre, or ſpeaking from, or to a particular text; for I am not againſt it: but onely, this your making ties; where God doth not tie you, and cry up forms, more then the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Leave off the Idolizing of humane learning, and uſe it onely in its place; then you will look upon it as convenient, but not of abſolute neceſſitie: it will inable you with expreſſions, but not with ſpirituall interpretations. Never think that you know more of the minde of Chriſt than others, becauſe you know more of of the ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues than they: Alas! take all the learning, arts, parts, in the whole world, and give them together into one man; yet this man by all his parts, wit, and arts, in Logick, tongues, and phyloſophie, is unable to give a true ſpiritual ſence of one of the eaſieſt and plaineſt ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. The ſpirituall myſterie is ſo high, he cannot reach it; ſo deep that he cannot fathom it; ſo long, he cannot meaſure it; and ſo broad, that he cannot comprehend it. Hence it is, that many in our daies, are great ſchollers in humanitie, and meer ignorants is divinitie. Was not <hi>Paul</hi> a great ſcholler, as he teſtifieth of himſelf; and yet igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Chriſt, knowing nothing of the ſpirituall ſence of ſcriptures. O you ſchollers, have you been ſo long at <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> (the two eyes of our land) and can you not ſee without Spectacles: have you been at the fountain, and muſt the ſtreams teach you? Doe you not know, that there is a ſpirituall learning as well as a humane? If you do know it, why do you give, a falſe interpretation of moſt ſcriptures; taking them in the litterall, when they are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, in the ſpirituall ſence. To inſtance, in one for all, 2 Pet. 3.16. <hi>There are ſomethings hard to be underſtood, which they that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:165154:21"/>wreſt, as they doe alſo other ſcriptures to their own deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Now the queſtion is, of thoſe things in <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, which <hi>Peter</hi> here ſpeaks of, as hard to be underſtood, and which the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant did wreſt, the queſtion is: What is meant here, by <hi>unlearned?</hi> Doth hee mean unlearned in humane, or unlearned in ſpirituall things?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Mee thinks the Apoſtle in the ſame verſe, reſolves the ſcruple.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For, firſt it is ſaid, <hi>Paul wrote theſe things according to the wiſdome given unto him;</hi> which is not meant wiſdome of the world, for God doth accompt that but fooliſhneſſe (ſaith the ſcripture) and <hi>Paul</hi> renounced it alſo, and ſaid; <hi>I came not with excellency of words, or of wiſdome, ſhewing unto you the teſtimony of God: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſtood my Word and Preaching, in the enticing ſpeech of mans wiſdome; but in plain evidence of the Spirit, and of power: that your Faith ſhould not be in the wiſdome of men, but in the power of God. And we ſpeak wiſdome, and not the wiſdome of this world, &amp;c. but we ſpeak the wiſdome of God in a myſtery, even the hid wiſdome, &amp;c. which the Princes of this world have not known, &amp;c. But God hath revealed them unto us, by his ſpirit, which ſearcheth the deepe things of God, &amp;c. and which we have received, that we may know the things that are given to us of God, &amp;c. Which things alſo wee ſpeak, not in the words which mans wiſdome teacheth; but which the Holy Ghoſt teacheth, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Cor. 2. chap. throughout; which you ſee doth abundantly teſtifie, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake not according to humane learning: reade alſo 1 <hi>Gal.</hi> 12.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Peter,</hi> here ſaith, that one of thoſe difficult ſayings of <hi>Paul,</hi> which the unlearned underſtood not, was this; <hi>That the long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of our Lord is ſalvation;</hi> which being a ſpirituall thing (as all the things of ſalvation are) cannot be underſtood by natural wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; for the things of God, <hi>knows no man, but the ſpirit of God:</hi> therefore <hi>Pauls</hi> wiſdome was ſpirituall, and their <hi>unlearnednes,</hi> there ſpoken of, was this; that they had not that wiſdome, in which he knew ſalvation; that is, the wiſdome of God: for worldly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome they might have, and bee nevertheleſſe ignorant of all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, They were unlearned, that is, they had not the learning, by which they might underſtand thoſe things in the ſence which would tend to their ſalvation, or true knowledge of God; and that,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:165154:22"/>ſurely is onely a ſpirituall ſence: For elſe to wreſt it to another ſence, could not be to their deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Peter</hi> here exhorts the Saints, to take heed of that errour of the wicked, leaſt they alſo ſhould be lead away with it, accounting it (you ſee) a wicked errour. And then in the next place, exhorts them to <hi>grow in grace, and in the knowledge of Chriſt,</hi> as being a thing contrary to that wicked errour, and a remedy againſt it. Now <hi>if the knowledge of Chriſt and growing in grace,</hi> be a remedy againſt that errour; then, it is moſt plain, That their unlearnedneſſe (which is there ſaid, to be the cauſe of their errour) was not of humane tongues and ſciences (for then <hi>Peter</hi> would have bidden them ſtudie theſe to keep them from errour:) But it was of the grace of God, and of the knowledge of Chriſt they were ignorant or unlearned; and therefore he bids them grow in that grace and knowledge, that they might not erre.</p>
               <p>So that that ſaying of <hi>Peter</hi> being thus truly underſtood; it is moſt plain that their unlearnedneſſe which cauſed them to erre, was their ignorance of Grace, and of Chriſt, not of humane learning:</p>
               <p>To which alſo let me adde theſe rules, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, That a mans principle, by which he doth converſe with (or apprehend) any thing; muſt be of a nature ſuitable to the nature of that thing which he converſeth with or apprehendeth; as in particular,</p>
               <p>You cannot apprehend or diſcover any object of ſence, by the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of reaſon; for example, you cannot by your reaſon (or any thing elſe, but your ſence of hearing) apprehend or know, that there is any ſound or noiſe, nor how it ſoundeth. But the care and voice are ſuitable: not a voice and another ſence, as, we cannot ſee a voice, &amp;c. Juſt alike impoſſible it is for reaſon (meerly naturall) to know ſpirituall things, as the ſcripture ſaith, <hi>the naturall man knows not the things of God:</hi> nature hath not a power ſuitable to attain to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Second rule,</hi> Every evill or defect is remediable, onely by its contrary good, or ſupply; as darknes is remediable by light, carnal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by ſpiritualneſſe, weaknes by ſtrength, ignorance by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Which two Rules (if you obſerve them) will help to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of thoſe words of <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if yet you are perſwaded that your Univerſitie learning can
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:165154:22"/>dive into the ſpirituall ſence of ſcripture, I would propoſe to a whole Synod of your function to reconcile theſe Scriptures hereafter cited, that are in the letter ſo contradictory one to another, for inſtance,</p>
               <p>One Scripture ſaith, <hi>Thou muſt love thy Father, Mother, Wife, Children</hi> &amp;c Another Scripture ſaith, <hi>Thou muſt hate all theſe if thou wilt be my diſciple</hi> Luke 14.26. One Scripture ſaith of God, <hi>Anger is not in me:</hi> Another ſaith, <hi>He is angry with the wicked e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day,</hi> Pſal. 7.11. One ſaith, <hi>Yee doe alwaies reſiſt the holy Ghoſt,</hi> Acts 7.51. Another ſaith, <hi>They could not reſiſt the Spirit by which he ſpake,</hi> Act 6.10. Another Scripture ſaith, <hi>That he that ſaith he hath not ſinned, is a lyar and the truth is not in him,</hi> 1 John 1.8.10. One Scripture ſaith of <hi>John, That he was not</hi> Elias, <hi>John</hi> 1.21. Another ſaith of the ſame <hi>John, That he was</hi> Elias, Math 11.14. Matth. 11, 12.</p>
               <p>I might inſtance in at leaſt 40. Scriptures thus contradictory in the letter.</p>
               <p>Now this is the thing that I would aske you, whether through the underſtanding of tongues or arts humane, you can give the true genuine ſence of thoſe Scriptures? ſurely you cannot, for theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures were pend by the holy Spirit, whoſe myſterious language, the eare of man naturall cannot heare, nor his heart conceive much leſſe his tongue expreſſe or interpret.</p>
               <p>To conclude, you doe ignorantly looke upon your ſelves as ſo many learned Apoſtles, now conſidering that there are many <hi>Aquillas</hi> and <hi>Priſcillas</hi> that can teach you the way of God more plainly. Read and well conſider that <hi>Acts</hi> 18.25, 26.</p>
               <p>That place of <hi>Peter</hi> about the unlearned, hath led me to a long digreſſion, but now to returne againe to adviſe you.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Lay aſide or leave off your kindling of flames in the State, and blowing the bellowes of contention and vaine jangling, and fall to preaching the Goſpel of peace: Let the State Governours alone with the State affaires. And alſo let the Lord Chriſt alone with the diſcipline of his Church. Let it not be ſaid of you as once it was of the high-Prieſts, that they were the onely enemies to the Kingdome of Chriſt, and yet the great pretenders to it. Doe not reproach the Lords people as once they did, for beleeving in and following of their Lord Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>Have any of (us) the Rulers beleeved on him?</hi> No, none (ſaid they) but a few ignorant people that know not the law. Doe not accuſe the Lords people in your Pulpits, as the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:165154:23"/>Prieſts did <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 24.5. ſaying, he was a peſtilent fellow; <hi>amover of ſedition, and a ring-leader of the ſect of the Nazarens.</hi> Leaſt the Lords people ſhould anſwer you as <hi>Paul</hi> did them, <hi>Acts</hi> 24. v. 14. <hi>After the way which you call hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So having ſpoken of the things that you muſt lay aſide, or forſake; Give me leave, as briefly as I may, to lay before you a few things that you ought immediatly to practiſe; I ſay, immediatly: becauſe it is high time, if you have not ſtaid too long.</p>
               <p>Firſt, If you be the Miniſters of Chriſt, obſerve your Commiſſion given you <hi>Mark</hi> 6.15. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. The ſumme of which is this, Go yee to all the world and Preach the Goſpel to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; And <hi>Paul</hi> elſwhere gives an account of his commiſſion, and ſaith, Chriſt ſent him to preach the Goſpel, and ſo he went Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peace by Jeſus Chriſt. Seeing God in theſe latter dayes ſpeaks unto us by his Son <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. Why do you ſpeak ſo much by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> you ſay <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt prepare us for Chriſt ſure that is not in Your Commiſſion: Me think I hear you ſaying with <hi>Peter;</hi> Maſter, let us build here three tabernacles, one for <hi>Moſes,</hi> one for <hi>Elias,</hi> and one for thee; and there appeared a bright cloud, upon the appearance of which, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> (which was <hi>John Baptiſt</hi>) vaniſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And God anſwered <hi>Peter</hi> from heaven, and told him, <hi>This is my beloved ſonne: heare him.</hi> Why do you then build a taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle for <hi>Moſes,</hi> and another for <hi>Elias,</hi> ſeeing the bright cloud hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled the dark adminiſtrations of them both.</p>
               <p>O then follow the adviſe of Chriſt, and keep cloſe to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; and into whatſoever houſe you enter, let your firſt words be, <hi>Peace, to this houſe,</hi> Luke 10.5.</p>
               <p>Why doe you teach repentance before Faith, ſeeing true and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned repentance is a fruit of Faith, not a preparation for Faith. The <hi>Ninevites</hi> believed God before they proclaimed a Faſt: and thou muſt firſt look upon Chriſt, whom thou haſt peirced, by Faith; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou canſt mourn, as one mourneth for his onely Son. The good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God will lead thee to repentance. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. <hi>And the grace of God will teach thee to deny ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts,</hi> 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>Faith is a notable ground-work, in a ſence of true repentance; without this Faith, it is in vain to think to build up our ſelves in ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity of life, and ſincerity of converſation; For <hi>he that commeth to God muſt firſt believe, that God is: Heb.</hi> 11.6. And without this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:165154:23"/>Faith, it is impoſſible to pleaſe God: and whatſoever is not of <hi>this Faith is ſin,</hi> Rom. 14.23 My friends, is not faith the firſt ſtone in the ſpirituall building, the firſt ſtep in a Chriſtian race, the firſt linke in our golden chain of Chriſtianity, the firſt act of our new life, the firſt degree in our holy converſation, the firſt round in your <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder, wherby you aſcend up into the preſence of your Lord? Should you not acquaint your hearers firſt with the doctrinall part of Divinity, before you preſſe the practicall part; endeavour to have them truly prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled, and then preſſe obedience as the fruit of thoſe principles; I have heard ſome of <hi>you</hi> ſay, that whatſoever obedience doth flow from any man; if it flow not from good principles, that obedience is in a ſence diſobedience. See what Chriſt commands <hi>Matth.</hi> 12 33 Make the tree good, and his fruit will be good, and good reaſon, for <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.18. a corrupt tree cannot bring forth good fruit. Now here is the reaſon, why you ſee ſo little fruit of all your labours? you preach ſo much, yet doe ſo little good: you do not doe Gods work in his own way; you preach and contend for order, and ſcarce are any in the kingdome more out of your order, than your ſelves. In a word, you require good fruit from a corrupt tree, and Chriſt tels you, it cannot bee. When <hi>David</hi> taught his ſon <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28 9. He inſtructs him firſt in the doctrinall part, before the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call part; He muſt firſt <hi>know the God of his Fathers,</hi> before he is preſt to ſerve him: This was <hi>Pauls</hi> adviſe, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.8. Again, our bleſſed Lord Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.4. exhorts the people firſt to abide in him; and being in him by Faith, then bids them bring forth fruit, ſaying, <hi>as the branch cannot bear fruit, except it abide in the Vine; no more can yee except yee abide in mee.</hi> So <hi>Paul</hi> dealt with the <hi>Colloſſians,</hi> 1 <hi>Coll.</hi> 9.10. He prays and deſires, firſt that they might be filled with the knowledge of Gods will; and then <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. (as the fruit of that knowledge) <hi>that they might walke worthy of the Lord, being fruit full in every good work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The next thing that you ſhould practice after you have exalted Chriſt alone, to be the onely King, Prieſt, and Prophet, not in word only, but in power; in expecting the teachings of God the father to your ſoules, by, and through him, have recourſe to his rules in the Goſpell for your practice: and then you will not look ſo much upon Synods, and not be aſhamed to confeſſe him before men: If you have been in the Pulpit delivering his meſſage, why are you ſo afraid to have your doctrine queſtioned? why will you not give your hearers that liberty, that Chriſt hath given them; to judge of what you have
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:165154:24"/>ſaid? are you aſhamed to own Chriſt, when his doctrine is examined? Or elſe, do you finde your ſelves unable by ſound doctrine to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the gain-ſayers. But you will ſay, If any be not ſatisfied, let him come to us in private; let me ask you: where have you a rule for that? do you not deliver your things publiquely? And do not the ſcriptures tell you, that a publique evill muſt have a publique reproof? But you will ſay, we have done no evill: we have preached Chriſt according to our commiſſion. Then (my friends) never fear to have it qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtioned: but (I beſeech you) if any can object againſt what you have taught, ſo he do it in the ſpirit of meeknes, rather to finde out truth, then to carp at truth: And ſeeing Chriſt hath given him that liberty. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. Do not you deprive him of it. If you would but make tryall of this; I will aſſure you, you might gain many privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges by it: In particular, I will ſhew your two or three.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You will take away all juſt occaſions, for any to cavill at your doctrine, or ſpeak evill of you in private.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You will increaſe your own knowledge; for there are ſome <hi>Aquila's</hi> and <hi>Priſcillas</hi> doe heare you: and you alſo may bee more inabled to inſtruct.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It will make the luſtre of the truths which you aſſert, the more beautifull, if you vindicate them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It will make all your ſayings ſeem the more worthy ſerious and ſober conſideration.</p>
               <p>O that I could ſee the miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> as willing to be taught, as they are to be teachers; as ſwift to hear, as to ſpeak: Truly, this were a way to untie the greateſt things we want in our kingdome.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When you have exalted Chriſt alone, and diligently obſerved his Commiſſion; next I beſeech you, be tender of his Lambs, and feed them; and ſo much the rather, becauſe they are yet ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the ſtreets of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and the Dogs of <hi>Egypt</hi> do bark at them: Oh ſend forth no more Dogges to bark and ſnap at the poor tender ones; for they have a tender father, the Almighty Lord God, that doth take all the injuries done to them, as done to himſelf; and takes notice of all the hard ſayings againſt them, as you may read at large in the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>But you will (as I have heard you) ſay, we ſpeak not againſt thoſe that are truly godly; but we cry out againſt blaſphemers.</p>
               <p>So was our bleſſed Lord Chriſt perſecuted, and reproached under the name of a blaſphemer. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.33.</p>
               <p>And ſo was <hi>Stephen</hi> (a man full of the holy Ghoſt, and of Faith) accuſed for a blaſphemer. <hi>Acts</hi> 6.13.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:165154:24"/>And they were great learned men that did this: and this is written for ſome to learn. Again, Chriſt was called a deceiver, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.6. And a Wine-bibber. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.19.</p>
               <p>It would be worth your labour, to examine from the beginning of the Bible to the end; how in all ages, and under all adminiſtrations, the Prieſts, and Levites, and pretended Miniſters, which would be known by the names of Prophets, Seers, Watchmen, or Leaders, and in this preſent generation above all others, have had their hands in (almoſt) all the Wars, diviſions, combuſtions, uproars, tumults, and troubles in the Kingdome. For matter of blaſphemy, hereſie, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, Idolatry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were not this tribe the ring-leaders, as alſo in perſecuting the Lords people: nay, the greateſt oppoſition that our Lord Chriſt himſelf met withall, was from that tribe; and have not they the chiefeſt hand in our preſent troubles, I leave to the whole kingdome to judge. Wherefore, my friends, conſider upon what ground you ſtand, and upon what foundation you are built: and let it be your ſtudie to put out, not to kindle flames in the kingdome; to heal the wounds with which we languiſh, not to make more. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member theſe words of Chriſt; <hi>Bleſſed are the peacemakers.</hi> Matth. 5.9. I know this is the practice of ſome of you; but truly, the number of ſuch is but few: yet I do believe there are, and ſo in all former ages, there were a few ſcattered up and down, that were true Prophets waiting upon God for an heavenly meſſage; and that they doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and declare unto this kingdome.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Seek not your maintenance in an unjuſt way: But caſt your ſelves upon the providence of God; as for the ſalvation of your ſouls, ſo alſo for the maintenance of your bodies; can you truſt God with a ſoul, more worth than ten thouſand words; and can you not truſt him with a little earth, your bodies. You teach us to pray for daily bread, and you do well: but muſt you ſelves take canal care for yearly bread; if not, what means this bleating of Sheep, and lowing of Oxen; your pleading for Tythes in your Pulpits. On my friends! bee yee ſure to doe Gods work; and I will pawn my life for him, he will pay you your wages: feed his Lambs, and your God will give you your meat in due ſeaſon: O let the ſame minde be in you, as was in your brother <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.15. where he renders three reaſons why he would not preach for money, not tythes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe he would not make his glorying voide, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe he would not make the Goſpel of Chriſt chargeable to them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:165154:25"/>3. He would not compell any to pay money or tythes for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, leaſt he ſhould hinder the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>How many ſuch <hi>Pauls</hi> have wee in our dayes; is there indeed one of a thouſand: yes, (my friends) there are through Gods goodnes (to my knowledge) a few.</p>
               <p>I ſpeak not in this againſt a juſt maintenance for a true miniſtery, for then I ſhould ſin againſt God and my own Conſcience; for I know God ſaith, he hath ordained that they that preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel: and my own conſcience tels me that if they have ſown unto me ſpirituall things, I ſhould not keep back from them carnall things. All that I here ſpeak againſt is this, your looking for your maintenance in an unjuſt way.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Give no offence unto any man, neither to Jew nor to Gentile, nor to the Church of Chriſt; but keep a conſcience void of offence both towards God, and towards man: be patient towards all, ſpeak evill of no man; ſeek the glory of God before your own honour, and the good of his people as your own good: and as you would that others ſhould doe unto and ſpeak of you, ſo do and ſpeak you of them; in all you actions, propound Chriſt, for your pattern; and learn of him, for he was meek and lowly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now to you called <hi>Independents.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I May ſay to you, as once <hi>Paul</hi> did to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.4. <hi>I thanke my God alwaies on your behalfe; for the grace of God that is given you by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Yea I may ſay to you as Chriſt did to the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Rev. 2.2. <hi>I know thy workes, and thy labour, and thy patience, and how thou canſt not beare them that are evill, and thou haſt tryed them which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not; and haſt found them lyars. And thou haſt born, and haſt had pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience under all thy reproaches; for thou haſt had many oppoſers, reproachers, ſlanderers, back-biters, and evill ſurmiſings againſt thee;</hi> if thou holdeſt to the end, and art willing to be a follower of Chriſt, as well in his humiliation, as in his exaltation; thou haſt a fellowſhip with him in the one, as well as in the other.</p>
               <p>Again, This I finde in thee (O thou <hi>Independent.</hi>) Thou deſireſt to walk by rule. When thou wouldeſt know the minde of God, thou lookeſt into the teſtimonies of his revealed will, the Old and New Teſtament; Thou groundeſt what thou holdeſt, upon that word;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:165154:25"/>thou accounteſt the principles and practices evill, that are not warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by that word: And if men come unto thee, and ſpeak with the tongues of men and angels, thou wilt (with the noble <hi>Bereans</hi>) ſeach the Scrip ures, to ſee, whether the things they ſpeak of be ſo or no; and if they ſpeak not, according to that rule, thou wilt preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude; it is, becauſe there is no light in them: Nay, thou knoweſt, that if a man come, and preach any other Goſpel than that which thou haſt received, 1 <hi>Gal.</hi> 8, 9. he is to be accurſed: and this thou haſt alſo (to thy commendation) the more others doe ſlight, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, and lay aſide the ſcripture, as a thing out of date; the more thou doeſt embrace it, read it, conferre, and meditate on it; and account it ſweeter than the honey, or the honey combe, and eſteem it (with <hi>Job</hi>) more than thy naturall food. Thou knoweſt right well, they were written for thy learning. Again, I may ſay of thee, as once it was ſaid of the Church of <hi>Pergamos,</hi> 2 <hi>Revel</hi> 12.13. <hi>I know thy works, and where thou dwelleſt, even where Satans ſeat is: yet thou holdeſt faſt Chriſts name, and haſt not denyed his Faith.</hi> Again, this thou haſt, that thou withdraweſt from every brother, that thou clearly ſeeſt to walk diſorderly; thou doeſt reprove, rebuke, and exhort with all long ſuffering. Again, this thou haſt; thou lookeſt to the ſpirituall growth of thoſe with thee: thy members watch over one another, and in love reprove one another, and many of you do it in the ſpirit of meeknes, as you would that they ſhould doe unto you in the ſame caſe, even ſo you doe to them.</p>
               <p>Again, This you have; you take a ſpeciall care of the poore among you, and you loath the unjuſt practices of ſome other Congregations of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> that gather a juſt maintenance for the Poore in an unjuſt way: They cut large thongs, but it is of other mens Hides: they doe not with Chriſt chooſe Deacons, but with Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt Collectors. Some of which muſt pay the Poore, and are ſure never to receive their money again, though they borrowed it for that purpoſe: but God be thanked (oh thou <hi>Independent</hi>) thou haſt not ſo learned Chriſt; thou knoweſt well, that the Lord loveth a chearfull giver, and accepts none but a Free-will offering: you give unto all, but have a ſpeciall regard unto the houſhold of Faith, according to rule. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10.</p>
               <p>Again, This thou haſt, thou forſakeſt not the aſſembly of Saints, as the manner of ſome is; you hear the Word in publique, and build up one another in private; you doe not (as ſome others) cry up the publique, and contemn the private; nor cry up the private in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:165154:26"/>of the publique: thou lookeſt into the Goſpel and findeſt both of them commanded and commended, and therefore makeſt uſe of both: Thou knoweſt that as God is no reſpecter of Perſons, ſo he is no reſpecter of places. Thou findeſt him teaching thee in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and alſo in private; abroad, and at home; thou findeſt him in the Fire to ſave thee, and in the Water to help thee, and in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to free thee: thou knoweſt thy God is in all places, and yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in no place.</p>
               <p>Now having thus taken notice of the things commendable in thee, according to that rule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 And as Chriſt dealt with the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> 2 <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.3.</p>
               <p>Give me leave alſo to deal plainly with thee, as <hi>Paul</hi> did. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.11, 12. and as Chriſt with <hi>Epheſus:</hi> and then, I ſhall not ſpare to tell thy Congregations and Members, that there are faults, amongſt you; therefore I have ſomewhat againſt you.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If you be not guilty of that ſin that <hi>Paul</hi> reproves the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> for 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.11, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. I am ſure you are guilty of that ſin that is reproved, 2 <hi>Jam.</hi> 2, 3.4. <hi>You have the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Lord of glory, with reſpect of perſons; for if there come into your aſſembly</hi> (as <hi>James</hi> faith) <hi>a man with a gold ring, and in goodly apparrell; and there come in alſo a poore man in vile raiment, you are apt to ſay to him in gay clothing; Sit thou here, (in a good place)</hi> and though you do not in plain terms or words, <hi>ſay to the poore, ſtand thou there, or ſit at my footſtoole;</hi> yet you let him ſtand at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or ſit at your feet: and <hi>James</hi> tels you, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Yee are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall.</hi> And many times thoſe poore ones whom you ſleight, God hath choſen; and the rich ones, whom yee honour, God hath rejected: verſ. 5. <hi>Hath not God choſen the poore of this world rich in Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You are ſtrange to thoſe that are called <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> which many of them being truly godly, you ſhould viſite; and if there be any way of wickedneſſe in them, reprove them; if they bee low in their principles, endeavour to raiſe them; and where they are imperfect in the way of God, teach them more perfectly: Love not one man, becauſe he is an <hi>Independent,</hi> hate none for being a <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian;</hi> for this were to know men after the fleſh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is utterly a fault among you in that many of you do fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion your ſelves according to this world; if there be any new foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh faſhion going, yee are in haſt to take it up with the firſt, quite contrary to the command of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.14. And as in your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:165154:26"/>ſo in your long haire; why doe you <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were it like <hi>Ruffians?</hi> It is true I know that as religion ſtands not in meat or drinke, ſo neither ſtands it in cloathes nor haire long or ſhort: But your abuſe of this doth diſhonour religion, grieve the Saints, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the world, eſpecially of the firſt of theſe, to wit, <hi>cloathes.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech you heare a few words further.</p>
               <p>Is your Kingdome or glory of this world or in things outward, or fleſhly, or even in vanity? Is it your worke appointed and your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light (yee Saints) to pleaſe the irrationall fancies of your fleſhly mindes? Can you who are ſo diſtinct and diſtant in your principles from the carnall and ungodly, ſo ſuite and conforme to them in thoſe things whoſe very fountaine or cauſe is none other but ignorance of God, which alſo are rationally cenſured even of thoſe that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out? Have you not better enjoyments: no better kingdome than this? Is not your glory within? Is not the moſt excellent your ſatisfaction, his preſence in your hearts your great refreſhments? Union and converſation with him your heaven and bleſſedneſſe: Doe you walke as Chriſt did: Whoſe meat and drinke was to doe the will of his father, are you like him?</p>
               <p>And ſeeing your faſhions are coſtly, let me aske you, doe you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that God hath given you ſo much of his creatures for any ſuch purpoſe? Can you ſay to the Lord, we bleſſe thee in our ſoules that thou haſt given us theſe creatures, and diſpoſed our hearts by thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to uſe them thus? Did ever God call ſuch things ſacrifices well pleaſing to him? Or have you the creatures in ſuch ſuperabundance, or are better opportunities ſo ſcarce that you cannot better uſe them? doe you thinke ſo? Then harken hither.</p>
               <p>Here are many of us poore miſerable wretches, whoſe bodies pine for hunger and thirſt, and ſtarve with cold: Some of us are exiles and ſtrangers, ſome of us in priſon, ſome of us ſicke, ſome wounded, lame, ſome weake, ſome widdowes, fatherleſſe and friendleſſe. Here wee ſtand before you, yee ſee us, yee know us: and can you yet withold reliefe? Have you no bowels of compaſſion? Hath mercy taken wing and returned to her eternall fountaine that ſent her forth? Hath ſhee no tabernacle nor temple with men? Hath ſhe left all hearts to hardneſſe? Will ſhee not vouchſafe us any of her divine bounty now, but leave us deſolate, captives to neceſſities till they have purſued our fleſh to diſſolution? Where are theſe promiſes of our deare redeemer, <hi>to dwell with men to the end of the world.</hi> When ſhall the powrings out of the ſpirit of grace (promiſed) be? Or
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:165154:27"/>where are thoſe Temples of his habitation, that wee may goe unto them? Will no man ſhew us? Ah ſad! Oh dolefull caſe miſeries devoure us: and pitty is departed from us.</p>
               <p>Oh deare friends: Are there all theſe ſad cryes and teares, and yet doe your vaine pleaſures bewitch you to bee deafe? Awake, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, for now your Lord commands, goe heare what thoſe my (and your) poore membes ſay, ſee why they weepe: <hi>Lord, they cry for want.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chr.</hi> What, want? And thou ſtand by with ſuch rich ſtores of mine? Oh moſt unfaithfull! Moſt unkinde! Doeſt thou love me: and doe I hunger in my members? and wilt not feede me with mine owne? but imbeſſell thoſe my ſtores to ſuch baſe Harlots as thy fleſhly fancies. Ah unfaithfull wretch, get hence, thou ſhalt not ſtay with me, nor ſee my face theſe many dayes. I deſire you to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether Chriſt doth not ſpeake thus to your Spirits. But I have digreſſed and now I returne.</p>
               <p n="4">4 This is alſo a fault among you, that you doe not pitty the poore blinde world, and endeavour to bring them into the knowledge of the truth, by laying before them the free love of God through Jeſus Chriſt; all your ſtudies are how to build up Saints, therefore to them you doe altogether ſpeake: Nay I have heard Sermon after Sermon in publique, beſides your practice in private, and you ſpeake onely to Saints enlightened, though moſt of the people to whom you ſpeake are yet in the old man, and have neede of ſuch a Sermon as <hi>Chriſt</hi> preached to <hi>Nicodemus.</hi> And ſo you are blame-worthy as the Presbyterians are, yea more than they, for many of them doe teach the practicall part of divinity before the doctrinall; and you tell of great enjoyments, before your hearers are truly principled; he that doth truly preach the Goſpell muſt preach to ſinners to convince them, as well as to Saints, to confirme them. If you will indeed be followers of Chriſt, you muſt not content your ſelves to preach a piece of the Goſpell, for Chriſt when he came among ſinners he was intreating and perſwading them and calling them to come to him that they might have life; He often encouraged them to come to him, telling them, he <hi>came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi> He bids come unto him, <hi>all you that are weary and heavy laden,</hi> and he will <hi>give you reſt:</hi> And ſaith, <hi>They that come to me I will in no wiſe caſt off.</hi> And when he gave his Commiſſion to his Diſciples, he told them, they muſt preach the Goſpell <hi>to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> Oh then pitty the world, pray for the world, rebuke, inſtruct,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:165154:27"/>exhort, perſwade, and beſeech them to be reconciled to God: your father lets the Sun ſhine and the Rain fall upon them, and bids you learn of him to love them.</p>
               <p>Doe they revile thee? Then with <hi>Paul, bleſſe them,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12. Doe they perſecute thee? Then with him ſuffer it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12. Do they take away thy cloak? give them thy coat. Doe they ſmite thee on the one cheek? offer the other.</p>
               <p>Do they curſe thee as <hi>Shimei</hi> did <hi>David?</hi> Then as <hi>David,</hi> let them alone: It may be the Lord hath bid them doe it. To you it is given, in the behalf of Chriſt; not onely to believe, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake: And how knoweſt thou, but that he will reward thee good for all their evill. If thou wer'ſt of the world, the world would love thee; but becauſe he hath choſen thee out of the world, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world doth hate thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Word to thoſe that goe under the name and title of <hi>ANABAPTISTS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY Brethren, there are theſe things worthy of commendation among you.</p>
               <p>You meet often together, and when you come together, as good Stewards of the manifold grace of God; as every one hath received the gift, ſo he doth adminiſter the ſame: you exceed, in ſome ſort, all other Churches, namely in this; That you doe adminiſter a right ordinance to right objects: you will doe God work in Gods way, I mean, you Baptiſe thoſe to whom Baptiſme belongs; you do that which is required, and as it is required. And in ſome meaſure you doe according to the command of Chriſt, 1 Theſſ. 5.14. <hi>You warn them that are unruly: you doe comfort the feeble minded, ſupport the weake;</hi> and in ſome meaſure yee endeavour to have patience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all men. And when men begin to deny, or ſleight Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, you withdraw your ſelves from ſuch; and this alſo is found in you, for which, I commend you: You look upon the ſcripture, as written for your learning; and therefore you often read, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of it; you cannot bear with thoſe that ſlight it, and ſpeak reproach fully of it: you have experience, that God doth teach you by his word mediately, more than by immediate revelations.</p>
               <p>But, my Brethren, there are faults among you; therefore I have
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:165154:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:165154:28"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:165154:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:165154:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:165154:30"/>a few things againſt you, wherefore bear with me, if I deale plainly with you: firſt, the Scripture bids you ſpeak evill of no man; why then doe you imagine in your hearts, and ſpeak evill of the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> becauſe he will not be rebaptized? Why doe you ſo judge the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> for Baptizing children, to whom it doth not belong. They doo not ſee by your eies, therefore they cannot walk by your ruks: are they in darkneſſe in this? ſo once waſt thou: Doeſt thou out-ſtrip them in this? it may be (nay I am ſure) they do go beyond thee in other particulars of obedience: Doe they neglect the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Baptiſme? that is their evill; but thou doeſt reſt upon it, and this is thy evill: do they ſin in ſleighting Baptiſme, thou ſinneſt in idolizing of it: Oh then, be ſparing to cenſure, and judge thy Brother!</p>
               <p>Here is another branch of your miſcarriage; you ſuffer no man (though never ſo well gifted) to ſpeak among you: no, though he be able to teach you all, unleſſe he be joyned to you by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Baptiſme with water, and though he be baptized with the Baptiſme of the Spirit, without which that of water is nothing; you hear him not.</p>
               <p>Again, you often take Scripture in the literall, when you ſhould take it in the ſpirituall ſenſe; When Chriſt ſpeaks of the baptiſme of the Spirit, you underſtand it to be of Water: In a word</p>
               <p>You live much under the adminiſtration of <hi>John,</hi> who tels you, that he muſt decreaſe, but not ſo much under the adminiſtration of Chriſt who ſhall encreaſe.</p>
               <p>Again, you make Baptiſme the ground of your communion, and ſo diſorder, what God hath ordered; for the ground of communion ſhould ariſe, firſt, from that union you have with Chriſt your head; and ſecondly, from that near relation you have each to other, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one in the ſame ſpirit: In a word, your knowledge that you have one of another, is after the fleſh: when will you be of <hi>Pauls</hi> minde, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16: <hi>to know no man after the fleſh:</hi> I may truly ſay of you, as once it was ſaid of <hi>Apollos, Acts</hi> 18.25. that he was inſtructed in the way of the Lord; knowing onely <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſme of water: and ſurely you have great need as once he had, to have <hi>Aquilla</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> to take you aſide, and teach you the way of God more perfectly, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:165154:30"/>
               <head>A Word to thoſe that hold <hi>Free-Will,</hi> and <hi>General-Redemption.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY Friends, ſome things I have obſerved from you, by my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among you; which I deſire to learn of you, and for which I commend you: I have ſeen you bearing one anothers burthens, relieving one anothers neceſſities, according to your abilities, often viſiting one another, with many outward expreſſions of that inward love, which you bear one to another, theſe things ought to be done; and there are other things which you ought not to leave undone; as alſo to love thoſe that are not under your form.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Principles alſo do you hold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, That Jeſus Chriſt gave himſelf a ranſome for all; and you prove it by Scriptures, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 6. 1 <hi>John</hi> 29. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.15.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That remiſſion of Sins ought to be preached to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; which proves the firſt, that Chriſt gave himſelf a ranſom for all; and therefore remiſſion of ſins muſt be preacht to all, and that you prove by theſe, and the like Scriptures, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.47. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15 <hi>Luke</hi> 10.5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.22.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That every one is to believe the forgiveneſſe of his ſins; for if Chriſt died for all, and the Goſpel ought to believe, and that all are called upon to believe: you bring theſe and the like Scriptures, <hi>John</hi> 1.7. <hi>John</hi> 17.21. Now if your principles drawn from theſe or the like Scriptures, be according to the ſpirituall ſence of them; you doe well: So much for the things worthy of commendation in you.</p>
               <p>But my friends, there are many faults among you, for which I have at preſent, a few things againſt you.</p>
               <p>The firſt, is your abuſe of Scriptures: firſt, in taking them in a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall ſence; ſecondly, looking into, and ſpeaking of onely thoſe ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, that ſeemingly in the letter doe confirm your principles: Whereas if you rightly underſtood them, you would finde the ſence of one ſcripture to ſtand with the ſence of another; As to inſtance a little in the forenamed things.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:165154:31"/>Firſt, you ſay, That Jeſus Chriſt gave himſelfe a ranſome for all, and remiſſion of ſins is to be preached to all: Now compare thoſe ſcriptures with <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. where he ſpeakes of particular, not of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall predeſtination. So when he ſpeakes of election to the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> he points at a particular, not at a generall election. And when Chriſt prayes <hi>John</hi> 17. hee prayes not for the world, but onely for thoſe whom the Lord had given him out of the world. And <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44. <hi>There can none come to him but whom the father draweth.</hi> Read and well conſider that one Scripture, which all of you are not able to anſwer, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. <hi>And as many as were ordayned to eternall life believed.</hi> I know what falſe gloſſe you put upon this text through your ignorance; you ſay the originall ſaith thus, <hi>As many as believed were ordayned to eternall life.</hi> And with this falſe ſence you deceived me for a few dayes, but when I ſearched the originall, I found you lyars, for that word is truly tranſlated; and I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with many poore ſoules that you have deluded with theſe and the like things. You ſay election depends upon qualifications and bring theſe or the like Scriptures, <hi>The Lord chooſeth to himſelfe the man that is righteous,</hi> never minding that other text which ſaith, there is <hi>none righteous no not one.</hi> So then, if he chooſeth none but the righteous, and there are no righteous, not one, then he chooſeth none. Oh you ſimple ones, how long will you love ſimplicity? Scorners delight in ſcorning? and Fooles hate knowledge? If this text doth ſpeak to any ſuch in <hi>England</hi> this day: It ſpeaks to, and concerns you chiefly.</p>
               <p>Did you never reade with underſtanding that text which ſaith, that wee and all the Nations of the World are in the hands or God, as clay in the hands of the potter, who maketh one veſſell to honour, another to diſhonour as he pleaſeth: And if there bee any man ſo impudent to ſay, as I have heard ſome of you ſay, that then God is partiall. See how <hi>Paul</hi> checks ſuch, Rom. 9.19.20. <hi>Oh man who are thou that replyeſt againſt God, ſhall the thing formed ſay to him that formed it why haſt thou made me thus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou wilt know a reaſon why the Lord doth elect ſome to life and to paſſe by others, he is pleaſed to give thee no other accompt than this Exod. 33.19. <hi>I will be gratious to whom I will be gratious, and I will ſhew mercy to whom I will ſhew mercy; and whom he will he hardeneth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou wilt alſo know a reaſon why he will caſt ſome into the pit of deſtruction, and give to others life everlaſting: I anſwer,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:165154:31"/>God hath no rule to act by but his owne will, ſo that for him to doe what he willeth, is juſt, and it is juſt for no other reaſon nor upon any other ground, but this, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe it is his will to doe it, and this is the juſtnes of mans actions, to doe what God hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or declared that he will have man to doe. Now I ſay, this is the reaſon why he will caſt ſome to deſtruction, <hi>viz.</hi> to magnifie his juſtice, or perform his will determined upon ſuch as doe tranſgreſſe the law given them, and for this cauſe is ſuch deſtruction juſt, becauſe it is that which the eternall will or decree hath appointed to follow upon tranſgreſſion. And after the very ſame ſort doth he exalt the attribute of his mercy in the ſalvation of others. Reade the 9. of the <hi>Romans</hi> and thou wilt finde moſt of that chapter ſpent in diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this very thing.</p>
               <p>Another groſſe error that you hold contrary to the ſcripture is this, That the ſoule is mortall as well as the body.</p>
               <p>Againe you hold and teach, That if God commanded the Goſpel to be preached to all, and Chriſt dyed onely for ſome, then God commands a lye to be preached to the moſt part of men, and that is blaſphemy to ſay that God commands a lye to be preached.</p>
               <p>Againe, You ground your owne particular faith upon that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall redemption, and if your ground be falſe, your faith muſt needes be ſo; for no good fruit proceeds from a corrupt tree; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doth ſuch faith exceede that of the Devils, that beleive and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>You ſay there is a power in every man to doe whatſoever is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, a power to chooſe and a power to refuſe; you cite that of <hi>Joſhuah</hi> and the like ſcriptures. <hi>Behold I have ſet before you this day, life and death, chooſe you whether</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ergo</hi> (ſay you) the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have power to chooſe and to refuſe.</p>
               <p>You ſay alſo that upon your doing, or not doing, depends your eternall bleſſing or everlaſting curſing, and yet unleſſe it be in ſome few things which I have fore-ſpoken in your commendation, you are the moſt unfruitfull people that ever I came amongſt, except our new upſtart wantons or new <hi>Notioniſts</hi> (to whom I ſhall ſpeake next.) You ſpend the moſt of your time, in ſpeaking evill of almoſt all other Chriſtians that walke not by your rules, and hold not to your errours, you back-bite and reproach them with that bitterneſſe of ſpirit, as is more ſuitable to the principles of Heathens than of Chriſtians, I will forbeare to ſpeake the one halfe of what I have beene an eye witneſſe unto of this kinde, in that little time when I
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:165154:32"/>was among you. You ſpend your time to ſpye a Mote in your Brothers eye, but when will you pull the Beame out of your owne eyes.</p>
               <p>Againe, You hold that a man may fall from Chriſt or Grace, you have often affirmed that a man may bee a childe of God to day, and a limbe of Satan to morrow, that he ſtands by obedience and not by grace.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>When he doth well he is accepted.</l>
                  <l>When he doth ill be is rejected.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And ſo by your errours, our ſalvation ſeemeth to depend upon workes, and ſo the free grace of God is nullified, and the obedience of Chriſt made of none effect; and in effect you plainly deny Chriſt: In a word,</p>
               <p>You hold more fooliſh, ſottiſh, unſound, unwarrantable, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable points; than any Sect; And your converſation is juſt anſwerable to your principles, ſo joyne both together and behold their ill ſhapen forme and fruit. 1. By them both you diſhonour God. 2. You grieve his people. 3. You delude the world 4. You cauſe the way of truth to be evill ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Remember therefore from whence you are fallen and repent or elſe the Lord will come unto you quickly, and fight againſt you</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A word to the new upſtart Wantons that deny Gods Ordainances, or New <hi>NOTIONISTS:</hi> full of Whimſies.</head>
               <p>MY Freinds, I have ſpent a few dayes and made diligent ſearch to finde ſomething in you worthy of commendation, that ſo I might ſpeake to you as I have to other Churches, taking notice of your Good and of your evill, but (my Friends) I cannot finde any thing among you but blaſphemy and hereſie, and truſting in lying vanities. Therefore as <hi>John</hi> ſaid in another caſe 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.3. I ſhall ſay to you in this caſe. <hi>That which I have ſeene and heard declare I unto you:</hi> and what I ſhall now charge you with, I have beene an eye and care witnes of, in converſing with you and being among you. Our Lord Chriſt speaking to the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> by <hi>John,</hi> diſcovereth in each of them ſomething worthy of commendation, but when he comes to the ſeventh Church, the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:165154:32"/>
                  <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> there was not ſo much as one graine of goodneſſe to be found in her: And yet this Church looketh upon her ſelfe as the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excellent Church, tranſcending all the reſt, Rev. 3.17. <hi>I am rich and encreaſed with Goods,</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>and have need of nothing, and knoweſt not that thou art wretched, and poore, miſerable, blinde, and naked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is thy ſtate to a haires breadth, oh thou New <hi>Notioniſt,</hi> thou lookeſt upon thy ſelfe as one gone beyond all others in high en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, and that can live upon God without uſe of ordinances, and worſhip God without formes.</p>
               <p>You ſay the Scriptures are not the word of God.</p>
               <p>Some of you have ſaid the Scriptures will teach you to lye, and ſteale, you ſay God cannot be diſhonoured by any Action you doe.</p>
               <p>And ſome of you have ſaid, the reaſon why they will not be drunk, is, becauſe they would not waſte their money and cauſe others to laugh at them, and becauſe it is hurtfull to their bodies, not for any diſhonour to God.</p>
               <p>You ſay, That the Scriptures doe not concerne you, that it is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a declaration of the Adminiſtrations that others have formerly beene under and worſhiped God in, you ſay there are one hundred and fifty lyes in it.</p>
               <p>You deny the reſurrection and the judgement, and ſay that there is no ſinne in the world, but that all actions are alike.</p>
               <p>You ſay that the higheſt enjoyment and perfection that a Chriſtian ſhall have, is in this life.</p>
               <p>You make your owne wils your rule, and when you are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed forth by them, you ſay you are carryed forth by the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>You ſay there are neither Angels nor Devils, but an adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, and an admiſtration of death, or one of light and another of darkneſſe.</p>
               <p>When you come together you ſpend your time for the moſt part in jeſting ſtories and Carnal merryment, and if any reprove you for it, you ſay you are carryed forth to it.</p>
               <p>You ſpeake evill of others that waite upon God in the uſe of means, you call them <hi>Legalliſts, Formalliſts</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Moſt of you deſpiſe to heare any Miniſter preach, though never ſo excellent a teacher.</p>
               <p>Some of you ſay that you can make better Bibles your ſelves, than
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:165154:33"/>that which is made already; ſaying, this Bible is but the opinions of men. You call Prayer, and all other Ordinances, bondage.</p>
               <p>You ſay, if one man kill another, it is God that doth it; yea, you can uſe deceipt in your particular Callings, and ſay, you do no evill.</p>
               <p>You care not for the weak, how you offend them; nor for the ſtrong, if you grieve them.</p>
               <p>And you above all other Sects in the world, cauſe the way of truth to be evill ſpoken off; moſt of the offences are come by you <hi>(wee be unto you)</hi> as ſaith the Scripture. The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> heare of your blaſphemies, errours, and abhominable things that you hold: and becauſe ſome of you were heretofore <hi>Independents,</hi> and ſome <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts;</hi> It makes the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> cry out ſo bitterly againſt the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> thinking them to be all ſuch as you are; when I muſt needs bear witnes for them both, they doe hate your principles, and practices, as they do the Devil, the father of them; In a word, you have turned with the Dog to the Vomite, and with the Sow to the wallowing in the mire.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, If there by any ſparks of grace remaining in you; If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, any comfort of love, if any fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels of mercies: then, oh then, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member from whence you are faln and repent!</hi> Learne of the Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Son, and come back again to your Father: for you have fed a long time upon husks, and your companions have been the Swine. You have back-ſlidden from your God, return to him again: It may be he will receive you: Seek meeknes, ſeek righteouſneſſe; it may be you may be hid in the day of the Lords anger. Waſh you, make you clean, put away the evill of your doings; ceaſe to doe evill, learn to doe well.</p>
               <p>There is alſo another ſort of people called <hi>Millenarians,</hi> who hold that Chriſt ſhall come, and Reign a thouſand years upon earth perſonally: But ſeeing the number of theſe is but few, and their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours (for the moſt part) but in circumſtantials, not in ſubſtantials; I ſhall at preſent omit to ſay any thing to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Word to another ſort of People, that are under none of thoſe Forms.</head>
               <p>THere are alſo a quarter part, if not more of the People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that are not under any of the aforeſaid formes; neither
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:165154:33"/>
                  <hi>Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, Free-willers,</hi> nor thoſe up-ſtart men of vanitie and emptie notions laſt mentioned; I ſay, They walk not, nor keep company with any of theſe, but a diſtance.</p>
               <p>And theſe are of two ſorts.</p>
               <p>The firſt is a precious, ſweet, moderate ſort of men and women, looking after and enquiring into the power and glory of truth, and godlineſſe, more than the forme: They clearly ſee all thoſe to whom I have ſpoken before, to be in extreams, either towards the right hand, or towards the left; and for the moſt part knowing Chriſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh; yet this ſort not under forms, look on thoſe that are under forms, for many of them to be (as indeed they are) members of the ſame bodie, whereof Chriſt is the head. Theſe men deſire to know no man after the fleſh; they love not any man becauſe he is a <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> neither do they hate another, becauſe he is an <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent;</hi> They deſire to have their moderation known unto all men, ſeeing the Lord is at hand: As theſe mens hearts are tender to all, ſo their Purſes are open to all. They deſire to be good, more than to be thought of others to be ſo; and eſteem the power of godlineſſe more than the form.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, there are another company, and theſe are the greateſt part, that are under none of the aforeſaid forms; who look upon all the reſt, and count it ſtrange, that they run not with them to the ſame exceſſe of ryot, ſpeaking evill of them all: The greateſt piece of theſe mens Religon is, to watch for the haltings of the reſt. Theſe men and women ſpend their time, for the moſt part, in gaming, drinking, back-biting, railing at all others, that will not doe as they doe. Theſe will not joyn themſelves with the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not love them: They will not come among the <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents,</hi> becauſe there they ſhall meet with reproof; they eſteem their liberty more than their Religion: therefore they keep compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with thoſe, where they may have their liberty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A few Words by way of Propheſie of the downfall of</hi> Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Independence, Anabaptiſme, Antinominiſme, Free-Willers, Vain-Notioniſts, <hi>and all other Sects now extant in</hi> England.</head>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:165154:34"/>
               <head type="sub">A word in generall to all the Saints, who are under any of the aforeſaid Forms.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>OH all you ſervants of the moſt high and mighty God, heires of Promiſe, and Sons of</hi> Sion; look for great alterations, and mighty changes, ſee what deſolations God will make in the earth, and looke for nothing but the Lord to be revealed from Heaven, which will be mighty in his diſpenſation and exceeding glorious in revelation, ſtrong and powerfull in operation. He will bring to paſſe his determination, that is, he will <hi>deſtroy in this Mountaine, the face of this covering caſt over all people, and the vaile that is ſpread over all Nations,</hi> Iſa. 25.7.</p>
               <p>If you aske what this <hi>vaile</hi> is, that ſhall be taken away.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, There are many vailes whereof this is one, <hi>thy knowing of Chriſt and Chriſtians after the fleſh:</hi> As ſoone as ever the Lord tooke this vaile of our deare brother <hi>Pauls</hi> eyes, ſee what a change it wrought immediately upon him, 2 Cor. 5.16. <hi>Henceforth know Ino man after the fleſh, yea though I have knowne Chriſt after the fleſh, yet henceforth know I him ſo no more.</hi> Our looking upon men and loving them becauſe they are under this or that forme, is a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them after the fleſh. <hi>Presbyterians</hi> looke upon others of the ſame judgement, worſhiping God in the ſame forme, and therefore love them. But let theſe ſpeake never ſo little againſt their forme, and preſently they caſt them out of their affections. and alſo the <hi>Independents,</hi> they know men after the fleſh much after the ſame manner: And likewiſe the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Free-willers,</hi> they are vailed with the ſame vaile. And therefore what I ſay to one Sect, I ſay to you all; you ſhall ſpeedily receive a totall rout: You have gathered your ſelves together, but you ſhall be ſeattered, yea you ſhall be broken in peices. Lo here is Chriſt, (the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> ſaith) in the publique ordinances, therefore highly eſteeme the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique preaching, and frequent the publique aſſemblies. Then comes in the <hi>Independent,</hi> and taking a ſtrict view of the <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> Way, ſees many diſorders amongſt them, and ſo ſeperates himſelfe from them, and joynes himſelfe to thoſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his owne judgement, and ſo meet in private, ſaying in effect, Lo here is, Chriſt, Lo here is Chriſt: Then ſtands up the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> in oppoſition to both, and ſaith, Chriſt is not with you in publique, nor with the <hi>Independent</hi> in private, But Chriſt is with us in the <hi>baptiſme of John.</hi> Lo, lo, here is Chriſt:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:165154:34"/>Then comes in he that holds generall redemption and free-will, and ſaith, Chriſt is among none of you all, for you doe eclipſe his free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, and limit his unlimited mercie, for he dyed for all, but you ſay it was but for ſome. 2. The Goſpel is to be preached to all, but yon ſay, though he preached it to all, yet he intended it only to ſome. 3. Whereas we hold that all ſhould beleeve the remiſſion of their ſins, you ſay, none can beleeve but a few that are elected. But we hold that as in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> all dyed, ſo in the ſecond <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> all are made alive. So that, if any periſh, let him thanke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for upon his obedience, or diſobedience, depends his weale or woe, and ſo God doth neither elect one, nor reprobate another, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath done good or evill. Lo here is Chriſt, here is Chriſt, ſay the <hi>Free-willers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo all other Sects, Lo here is Chriſt, ſaith one, Lo there is Chriſt, ſaith another, wherefore if they ſhall ſay unto you, Behold he is in the Deſart, Goe not forth, Behold he is in the ſecret Chambers, Beleeve it not.</p>
               <p>You all have built your outward houſe of externall diſcipline, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſand, and it muſt fall becauſe it is not grounded upon the rock Chriſt, you have made your communion the ground of your union, and that muſt fall, becauſe it is not the Lords but mans building</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But how doe you know that <hi>Presbytery</hi> muſt downe, and <hi>Independency, Anabaptiſme</hi> and the reſt of the Sects muſt downe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, Chriſt told the <hi>Jewes John</hi> 8.56. that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw his day and was glade Now if <hi>Abraham</hi> by faith did ſee the day of Chriſt, comming in the fleſh, many yeares before he came, why may not I and others ſee the day of chriſt comming in the Spirit to deſtroy all fleſhly formes, ſome few yeares before it be finiſhed.</p>
               <p>But if thou askeſt, How ſhall I know that thou propheſieſt true concerning the downfall of all theſe.</p>
               <p>I anſwer thee in this caſe, as the Lord himſelfe anſwered his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in another caſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.21.22. If thou ſhalt ſay in thine heart, How ſhall we know the word that the Lord hath ſpoken, from the word that he hath not ſpoken? The Lord there anſwereth, When a Prophet ſpeaketh in the name of the Lord, if the thing come to paſſe, it is from the Lord, if it come not to paſſe, it is not from the Lord.</p>
               <p>Againe, I have by faith ſeene all theſe opinions fallen, and I have
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:165154:35"/>heard from many others that they have ſeene them fallen alſo. Therefore that which I have heard and ſeene, declare I unto you, that you might have fellowſhip with the Father and the Sonne in the ſpirit, for then, and not till then, you will give over ſaying, as (in effect) you doe, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> I am of <hi>Appollo,</hi> I am of <hi>Cephas:</hi> Then you will not ſo much crye up a forme but endeavour the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of godlineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deliver thy ſelfe, then, oh</hi> Zion, <hi>that dwelleſt with the daughter of</hi> Babilon, Zecha 2.7. <hi>For the Lord ſhall ſlay</hi> Babylon, <hi>and call his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants by a new name,</hi> Iſa. 65.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſhort deſcription of a true Church-ſtate, or communion of Saints that ſhall ſtand againſt al oppoſers.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PAul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> writing to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> beſeecheth them in the name of Chriſt, that they would endeavour a perfect joyning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in one minde and one judgement, and good reaſon he had for ſo doing, for he well knew that all joynings whatſoever that were imperfect, were not of God, and ſo could not ſtand. In oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to all ſuch imperfect unitings or unſound communions, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades this Church of Chriſt, from pleading or ſtanding for patties, and from ſaying, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> I am of <hi>Apollos</hi> &amp;c. He doth in effect, tell them they muſt ceaſe from knowing Chriſt and Chriſtians after the fleſh, for that muſt vaniſh. He doth perſwade them not to build upon the ſand, for that will fall. The Spirit of Chriſt doth exhort you to give over ſaying, lo here is Chriſt, lo there is Chriſt, for that is unſound and cannot ſtand.</p>
               <p>That communion of Saints, that ſhall ſtand, againſt which the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile, let the winde blow, the raine deſcend and the floods come and beate upon it, it will not fall, for it is founded on a rocke. That communion then is this.</p>
               <p>A communion that doth ariſe or flow from union, I ſay, It is a communion of Saints, ariſing from a cleare apprehenſion of their u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13, 14. <hi>For by one Spirit are we all baptiſed into one body, whether we be Jewes or Gentiles, bond or free.</hi> And have beene all made to drinke into one ſpirit, for the bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s not one member but many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> verſe 20. <hi>For now are they many mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, yet but one body.</hi> Now when a Saint comes to ſee that every one in whom the Lord Jeſus appeareth, though in the leaſt meaſure, is a member together with him in the ſame body, whereof Chriſt is
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:165154:35"/>the head; then his heart longeth to joyne himſelfe in fellowſhip with ſuch, who have fellowſhip with the father and the ſon in ſpirit, whether in ordinances or otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>He conſiders that he and all the faithfull under the whole Heavens have all one father, all one mother, all one elder Brother, all one cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, all one hope of their calling, all cloathed with the ſame robe, all inclined to the ſame worke, all united by the ſame ſpirit, all ruled by the ſame word, and ſo he honours them all, as the body of Chriſt, and nouriſheth and cheriſheth them all, as his owne body. Oh who can breake the linkes of this golden chaine? Who can throw downe this ſpirituall building? No, no, The gates of hell cannot prevaile againſt it. Reade, and well conſider that in the 1 Pet. 2.5. <hi>Yee alſo as lively ſtones, are built up a ſpirituall houſe, an holy Prieſthood, to offer up ſpirituall ſacrifice acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt</hi> &amp;c. or as it is in the margin, <hi>be you built up a ſpirituall houſe.</hi> Goe now through all the Shires and Cities of <hi>England,</hi> and enquire, nay make diligent ſearch among all ſorts of people, profeſſing and pretending, to Chriſt, for ſuch a Congregation, that of lively ſtones hath built up ſuch a ſpirituall houſe, and note that Church: It ſhall never fall.</p>
               <p>Oh where is ſuch an aſſembly of Saints to be found, as is ſpoken of <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.22. that are built together for an holy habitation of God through the ſpirit. Shall I appeale now to thy very conſcience, and aske thee, oh thou zealous <hi>Presbyterian.</hi> Is your building which is ſo much cried up in <hi>England,</hi> ſuch a building?</p>
               <p>Shall I appeale now to thy conſcience, oh thou <hi>Independent;</hi> and aske thee, Art thou built up for an habitation of God through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſpirit? Doeſt thou indeed offer up a ſpirituall ſacrifice? Me thinks there is ſo much truth in both the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> and the <hi>Independent.</hi> as to anſwer in the negative.</p>
               <p>Well then, Hence it is you love one Saint, and hate another be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are not perfectly joyned together; You yet know Chriſt and Chriſtians after the fleſh, you have been joyned together in one forme, but not united together in one ſpirit. But the day is dawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before you, and the day ſtar is riſing in you, at the appearance of which your communion ſhall be in the ſpirit as well as in the forme, and your love ſhall be to all as well as to ſome, and when you are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in body (as <hi>Paul</hi>) you will be preſent in ſpirit, joying and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding their ſpirituall order.</p>
               <p>Now there are many reaſons why the Saints ought to bee thus joyned together: Take two,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe they are commanded to ſtand faſt in one ſpirit, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:165154:36"/>27. And how can they ſtand faſt in the Spirit if they be not joyned in the Spirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe that worſhip wherewith they muſt worſhip God, muſt be a ſpirituall worſhip, <hi>John</hi> 4.23.24. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</p>
               <p>And untill Saints are thus joyned together they are not fitly joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, according to that <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.16.</p>
               <p>Neither untill they be thus united in one ſpirit, can they be ſaid to have any fellowſhip of the Spirit, according to that <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1.</p>
               <p>Againe untill they be thus united in one ſpirit, how can they yeeld obedience to that command Ephes. 4 3. <hi>Endeavouring to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi> And that they might keepe the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace, ſee what power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full convincing arguments hee brings, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.4, 5, 6. <hi>There is one body,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and one ſpirit, even as yee are called in one hope of your calling: One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme: One God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi> Mark then (I beſeech you) the Lord by <hi>Paul</hi> doth here lay downe. 1. The uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thou haſt with him, 2. The union thou haſt with his people, and from both theſe, as from the ground, he puts his people upon a ſweet communion and fellowſhip both with himſelfe and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Upon this rocke hath Chriſt built his Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt a Church thus ſtated. But I have beene in communion with all ſorts of Profeſſors now extant in <hi>England,</hi> and waded out of one forme into another, and at the laſt I have clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found that much of their building, hath beene upon ſandy founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I ſhall then ſhut up all with one word of advice to all.</p>
               <p>Oh ye ſons of <hi>Sion!</hi> Behold your union with God, conſider alſo that yee are one, not with ſome (onely) but with all the Saints under whatſoever forme they be. Wherefore love them all, pitty them all, doe good to them all, and as you are united in one ſpirit, ſo let the the word and ſpirit be your rule. When you have gathered your ſelves together according to the order of the Goſpell, chooſe to your ſelves Paſtors, and Teachers, Elders, and Deacons, make uſe of all Gods ordinances but reſt upon none, looke upon them all but as Pipes and Organs through which he conveyes himſelfe to the ſoule <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But me thinkes I heare ſome ſay, What religion, or (at leaſt) opinion is he himſelfe off, that hath written this Treatiſe? He can be no <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> for he writes againſt them: He is no <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent,</hi> for he reproves them: No <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> for he diſlikes
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:165154:36"/>them: No <hi>Free-willer,</hi> for he writes directly againſt them: What then is he?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, I am a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>You will ſay, So are all the people of <hi>England,</hi> Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>But that I deny, For though there are many Chriſtians of mans making, yet there are few, yea very few of Gods making.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay, What are they then, if not Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, There are many Heathens, and Turkes, Jews, and Infidels many Canaanites, and Amorites, Perrizzites <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I am a Chriſtian, This name was given firſt to the diſciples in <hi>Antioch,</hi> I beleeve in one God, Father of all, and in one Lord Jeſus Chriſt redeemer of all, and in one ſanctifying Spirit of Grace; I beleeve that it is the office of the Father to elect, the office of the Sonne to redeeme, and the office of the Holy Ghoſt to Sanctifie thoſe and onely thoſe, whom the Father hath elected, and the Sonne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, And I doe beleeve my owne intereſt in all theſe, without which the knowledge of it is nothing; the Father loves me freely, the Son manifeſts that love to me, and the Spirit doth evidence it in me: The Father loveth me, as redeemed by his Sonne; The Son lookes upon me, and loves me, as being given by the Father, for him too redeeme; And the Holy Ghoſt ſeeing the love of the Father in chooſing me, and the love of the Sonne in redeeming me, he alſo ſets his love upon me, and manifeſts this unto me, which is the earneſt of my inheritance. I beleeve that God hath his being in himſelfe, and gives being to all other creatures, and the cauſe, why he made mee, was for his owne glory, and the end, why he elected me in Chriſt, was that I ſhould bring forth fruit to him, I know I am not my own I am bought with a price, wherfore I deſire to glorifie God with my body and my ſoule, which are the Lords. I endeavour, as to love God, ſo alſo to love his people, not ſome but all, and to love my enemies, deſiring to become all things to all that I might in my place gaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I doe bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to give no juſt offence to the <hi>Jew,</hi> nor the <hi>Gentile,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Church of Chriſt, wherfore as much as in me lieth, I endeavour to keepe a conſcience voide of offence both towards God, and towards man. I love all, and yet I deſire to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw my ſelfe from every brother that walketh diſorderly.</p>
               <p>I doe beleive that I am a Servant of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I doe beleeve I am a Friend of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 15.15.</p>
               <p>I doe beleeve that I am a Brother of the Lord Chriſt, <hi>Heb</hi> 2.11.</p>
               <p>I doe beleeve that I am in as neare relation to Chriſt, as the wife is to the husband, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:165154:37"/>I doe beleeve that I am a Member of his owne body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. verſe 12.</p>
               <p>I do beleeve that I am a Joynt-heire with Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</p>
               <p>I doe beleeve that I am joyned to the Lord, and ſo one Spirit with him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17.</p>
               <p>I doe beleeve that the Lord takes all the evill done to me, as done to himſelf, <hi>Zac.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.45.</p>
               <p>I doe beleeve that I have everlaſting life already, according to that <hi>John</hi> 3.36.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the promiſe, <hi>feare not little flocke, it is your fathers pleaſure to give you a kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In the firſt fruites, for what is heaven hereafter but a more full enjoyment of what is begun here.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I have everlaſting life already in poſſeſſion by my head Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I doe beleeve that all this is but a taſte of what I ſhall be, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that 1 John 3.1, 2. <hi>Now are yee the ſons of God, and it doth not yet appeare what you ſhall be. But when he ſhall appeare yee ſhall be like him.</hi> The ſerious conſideration of which, (I doubt not) will draw up my converſation more and more to be in heaven, even whil'ſt I remaine here on earth.</p>
               <p>I doe beelve that my ſinnes by Chriſt are taken out of the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>I doe beleeve that the deſigne of Chriſt was to take it away out of my Conſcience, that there might be no more conſcience of ſinne, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14.</p>
               <p>I doe beleeve that as Chriſt hath taken away ſinne out of the ſight of God, and out of my owne Conſcience, ſo in due time, he will take away ſin out of my converſation, according to that ſcripture 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. and <hi>Luke</hi> 1.75.</p>
               <p>In a word, I doe beleeve, my ſinnes paſt, preſent, and to come, are all laid upon and done away by Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6.</p>
               <p>I doe beleve that as there was no good fore-ſeene in me, that did cauſe the Lord to ſet his love upon me, ſo there is no evill that can be done by me, that can cauſe him to hate me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:165154:37"/>
               <head>A Word to the Parliament the Repreſentative body of the <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Cannot put a period to this little Volume, without one word to you, who are Members of the High Court of Parliament. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Worthies, you have begun well, go on that we may finde in <hi>England</hi> that that was ſo earneſtly ſought for in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Jer 5.1, <hi>Men executing judgement, and ſpeaking the truth:</hi> And then why may we not expect to be partakers of the mercy there promiſed; a pardoning of the ſin, and a healing of the Land. Eye the Lord Jeſus in all your actings, and advance his Kingdome, as much as in you lyeth: honour him and hee will honour you, and endeavour with <hi>David</hi> to deliver his Lambs out of the Lyons mouths, for they are tender in your Fathers eyes, let them be ſo in yours: Your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted courage in not fearing the faces of men, and your executing of juſtice upon all offenders, without reſpect of Perſons or partiality: as it is very acceptable in the ſight of God, ſo the ſound of it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſweet in the ears of his People. And as the Saints in <hi>England</hi> have put up many Petitions at the Throne of Grace, that God would give you undaunted Spirits; and having by experience found God anſwering their requeſt by your late actings, as touching the King and Lords; they are now turning their Prayers into Praiſes, to the Almighty for anſwering their Prayers in aſſiſting you. And the more difficulty you found in the work, the more God will honour you for the ſame.</p>
               <p>But Right Honourable Worthies, What ſhould be the cauſe that the people of <hi>England</hi> whom you doe repreſent; yea, they that have choſen you, and have ever ſince with their Lives and Eſtates aſſiſted you: What is the reaſon, that they all with one voice ſince the death of our late King are ſaying to you, as once the children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> to <hi>Rehoboam</hi> after the death of their King, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.4. <hi>Eaſe us of our heavy burthens, take away our taxations ſo heavy:</hi> and you have anſwered the people as <hi>Rehoboam</hi> did, if not in your words, yet in your deeds: ſaying, <hi>My little finger ſhall be heavier than my Fathers loins,</hi> and whereas you had a heavy yoak before, I will make it heavier: and whereas my Father chaſtized you with whipps, I will chaſtiſe you with Scorpions.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:165154:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:165154:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:165154:39"/>If you ſay, this is none of our anſwer, or practice; Let me aske you, What means the Exciſe, the doubled contribution, and Free-quarter, and many other grievous taxations and aſſeſſements: And when we conſider the time in which you encreaſe and continue theſe devouring Caterpillars, it doth aggravate your evill, as well as our ſence of the miſery; as to inſtance.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In a time when our trading at Sea is ſpoyled, and our Shipps daily loſt and taken.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In which our trading by Land is almoſt utterly decayed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In which all ſorts of proviſions for the nouriſhment of our almoſt famiſhed bodies is riſen almoſt to a double price.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Though what little Money and Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e we had, we lent before upon the Publike Faith; which proves a dead Faith, or at beſt, but a hiſtoricall Faith: For notwithſtanding all Promiſes, wee receive none of it back again.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In a time, in which many People are but, as it were newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to their Homes, after baniſhment for a long time from their habitations and eſtates, left to the cruell mercies of the adverſary.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In which many thouſands have had their Houſes burnt to aſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and cry for help to their neighbours that have eſcaped that calamity.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And laſtly, Which adds to our miſery more than all the reſt; In a time, when we expect a full deliverance; having by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Almighty power, gotten the victory over all our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: ſo that we may yet lament in the words of <hi>Jeremiah; Wee looked for Peace, and there is no good: and for times of Peace, and behold trouble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God hath put into your hands a power, if you have but hearts to make uſe of it, to take off theſe heavy burthens, wherewith your friends are laden.</p>
               <p>Are not the Crown Lands in your hands, and all the treaſures thereunto belonging: Are not alſo the Biſhops Lands in your hands.</p>
               <p>Are not all the Cuſtomes in <hi>England</hi> in your hands, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount ſo high.</p>
               <p>And alſo Delinquents Fines and Compoſitions.</p>
               <p>And yet muſt we have Exciſe remaine? and Contribution doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? Is this the reward that we ſhall have for all our Obedience to you? Oh conſider, conſider! To reward us evill for all our good, it is not ſound; and to make your friends your foes, it is not ſafe: Shall I acquaint you with what I know, and that upon ſound ground.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:165154:39"/>If the King had gotten the day, and all into his hands, as you have: would not he have freed thoſe that aſſiſted him? And have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his Armie upon the coſt of thoſe that did oppoſe him? did not his practiſe begin to teſtifie the truth of this? So tender was he of thoſe that aſſiſted him in his extremity.</p>
               <p>And will not you that profeſſe your ſelves to be the ſervants of Chriſt, and favourers of his people; doe as much for Chriſt, as hee for Antichriſt? Oh then! Oh then! let the coſt light upon thoſe that were the cauſe; and they that forced you to raiſe an Army, let their eſtates pay the Army.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
